<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Crosses case in Cheapside; vvhether its militia, the setting of it in a posture of defence, be according to law. The contrary is maintained by one, who hath little of that, we commonly call law; against those, who have as little of that, we truly call reason. Notwithstanding, the dispute is carried all along in a coole and orderly way, by the law of heaven, the line and rule of the Word, and as in Gods presence, who is judge Himselfe; so as the man in understanding may finde strong meate here; the childe milke.</title>
            <author>One who hath little of that we commonly call law.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E114_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17605</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860232</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860232</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112349</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112349)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 20:E113[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Crosses case in Cheapside; vvhether its militia, the setting of it in a posture of defence, be according to law. The contrary is maintained by one, who hath little of that, we commonly call law; against those, who have as little of that, we truly call reason. Notwithstanding, the dispute is carried all along in a coole and orderly way, by the law of heaven, the line and rule of the Word, and as in Gods presence, who is judge Himselfe; so as the man in understanding may finde strong meate here; the childe milke.</title>
                  <author>One who hath little of that we commonly call law.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in the climactericall yeare of crosses, and crosse-men. For T. V.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Milita --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cheapside Cross (London, England) --  Defenses --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112349:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE CROSSES CASE IN CHEAPSIDE; Whether its Militia, the ſetting of it in a poſture of defence, be according to Law. THE CONTRARY IS MAINTAINED by one, who hath little of that, we <hi>commonly</hi> call
<hi>Law;</hi> againſt thoſe, who have as little of that, we <hi>truly</hi> call REASON. <hi>Notwithſtanding,</hi> The Diſpute is carried all along in a coole and orderly way, by the Law of Heaven, the line and rule of the Word, and as in Gods preſence, Who is Judge Himſelfe; So as the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in underſtanding may finde
<hi>Strong MEATE</hi> here; The Childe <hi>MILKE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JER. 10.15.</bibl>
               <p>They are vanity, and the worke of errors: in the Time of their Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation they ſhall periſh.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ACTS 26.32.</bibl>
               <p>This Man doth nothing worthy of death, or of bonds.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ACTS 19.38.</bibl>
               <p>Wherefore if Demetrius, and the Craftsmen have a matter againſt any Man, the Law is open.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed In the Climactericall Yeare of Croſſes, and Croſſe-Men. For <hi>T. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:112349:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112349:2"/>
            <head>BY WAY OF PREFACE To the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hould I, in rendring an account of this <hi>Caſe,</hi> preſent thee with a <hi>Toy,</hi> it might paſſe with allowance; for experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tells us; That a <hi>Toy</hi> ſometimes makes a fuller diſcovery, what mens inclinations are, then a very ſerious matter can do.</p>
            <p>But ſurely this <hi>Caſe</hi> will be granted to be
<hi>ſad</hi> and <hi>ſerious</hi> both, if we conſult with <hi>Papiſt, Atheiſt,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant</hi> eyther: And, I verily beleeve, of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall concernment alſo, relating not onely to the
<hi>Street-Croſſe,</hi> but <hi>Highway, Church, Chappell, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, Window, Cloſet, Corner, Brow, Breaſt-Croſſes,</hi> all the Croſſes in the world, that are the worke of the cunning Crafts-man, or otherwiſe made with hands and the fingers ends to helpe devotion or for Religious uſe.</p>
            <p>And yet I have not named the <hi>Maſter piece,</hi> nor the
<hi>Maſter workeman;</hi> this is the <hi>heart,</hi> and that the
<hi>Idol</hi> there, ſet up in that place, where God ſhould have His Throne: (note in paſſage, an Idolater dethrones God) for in the
<hi>heart,</hi> the <hi>peace,</hi> the <hi>love,</hi> the <hi>feare of God</hi> ſhould beare ſway; and in token of victory over the <hi>Idoll</hi> there, <hi>beare away the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Palmam obtineat.</hi> Col. 3.15. Hoſ. 13.2.</note>, as the purpoſe of the word is. Were all the forementioned Idols (they are the worke of the Crafts-man, according to <hi>his own underſtanding</hi> odious to God and good men<note n="b" place="margin">God will have no worſhip of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing; wee may onely doe what He bids us; not bid what He commands not. Never did any true piety ariſe out of the corrupt puddle of mans braine: If it flow not from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, it is odious to Heaven. Doctor <hi>Halls</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. <hi>lib</hi> 12.</note>) were they all caſt
<pb facs="tcp:112349:3"/> out to the <hi>Moles</hi> and to the <hi>Bats,</hi> the heart would fetch them in againe, ſmooth them over and ſet them up before the eyes; for not onely theſe piles of Abominations, but every point of <hi>popery,</hi> had their originall draught in the heart, there they were firſt hatcht. In very deed the <hi>heart</hi> is a <hi>Common ſtew</hi> (no better;) therein you may finde the <hi>Popes Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell</hi> and
<hi>Maſſe-booke</hi> too. Therefore, though the <hi>Croſſe</hi> in the ſtreet, hath mooved the quarrell, and it ſhall be <hi>ſerved</hi> in its kind; one man or more hath <hi>(ſerved)</hi> defiled that <hi>Baal</hi> a
<hi>little,</hi> by the good word of God with me, I ſhall defile it much<note n="c" place="margin">2 King. 10.18.</note>: But yet, ſince the quarrell hath its <hi>riſe</hi> onely thence, with Gods helpe it ſhall be carryed on, to the defiling the Maſter worke, and its workeman, I meane the heart and the
<hi>Idoll</hi> there, for thereon will the Lord power forth the fury of His wrath, and the ſtrength of battle. And there is mighty Reaſon why it ſhould be ſo; for, to ſay all in a word; That Idol hath not onely
<hi>mated</hi> the God of Hoſts, ſetting up its ſelfe in His Throne, but alſo hath, doth, and will move all the quarrels in the world. Saint
<hi>James</hi> his queſtion can receive no other anſwer but his owne,
<hi>Whence comes warres and fightings among you</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">James 4.1.</note>? Hence, even <hi>from your Idols, your luſts that war in your members.</hi> That hath beene the anſwer, and that muſt be the anſwer to the worlds end. <hi>Divels</hi> and <hi>Idols</hi> doe all the miſchiefe in the world.</p>
            <p>But yet wee will not beleeve this, and it is a ſtrange matter, and as ſtrange a conceit, That we ſhould feele our <hi>Croſſes,</hi> feele them ſmart and ſore upon us, and not beleeve, that the <hi>Idol</hi> hath cauſed them. It is a weake and fond conceit too: as if we could thinke,
<hi>That affliction comes out of the duſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 5
6.</note> and trouble <hi>ſprings out of the ground: that the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:112349:3"/> 
               <hi>ruſh growes up without mire &amp; the flag without water.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 8.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I thought it very fit to mind thee (Reader) hereof on the threſhold, that thou mighteſt enter the houſe with more care and watchfulneſſe: for this will perſwade thee to beleeve; That the
<hi>Croſſes Caſe</hi> is a ſad and ſerious caſe, which now I ſhall open unto thee ſo farre, as may be ſutable to a Preface.</p>
            <p>You are not ſuch a ſtranger to our Occurrences, as not to have ſeene or heard what a ſtirre there was ſome moneths ſince, about the
<hi>Croſſe;</hi> what croſſing of ſhinnes, and of heads, and of backes, and of hearts too! What bloody noſes, and ſcratcht fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and back-blowes there were, and all about the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> to maintaine it according to its dignitie, in a poſture of defence.</p>
            <p>A man could not paſſe that way, but he muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelfe, <hi>whether for the Croſſe or againſt it;</hi> he muſt not conceale himſelfe in the Croſſes caſe, (as in good reaſon he might in ſuch a preſence but) if he did, he was <hi>Croſſed,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>One evening, hearing a noyſe thence, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from
<hi>Paris Garden,</hi> I ſtept up the ſtreet, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve my ſelfe, whether there were any <hi>Bulls</hi> and <hi>bayting</hi> there: and behold both; for there they ſtood as dogs at a Bay, bayting each at other; who? The Pſalmiſt anſwers, <hi>a company of ſpearmen</hi> (carrying their weapons in their mouthes<note n="a" place="margin">Pſa. 57.4.</note>) the
<hi>multitude of the Bulls,</hi> with the <hi>Calves of the People</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 68.30.</note>. <hi>Lord rebuke them</hi> ſaid I, and away I trudged; for truely I never liked to crowd-in amongſt unreaſonable Creatures, that cannot tell when, or how far to put forth their ſtrength, nor how to ſuſpend or call it back.</p>
            <p>But ſo every thing acteth according to its princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and I according to mine; So ſoone as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home, I examined the
<hi>caſe</hi> ſeriouſly &amp; hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily;
<pb facs="tcp:112349:4"/> and I iſſued the ſame, or rather the
<hi>ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> for me, thus; though I could not handle it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in the ſame order.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the defacing the Croſſe is an act juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the higheſt Law and in the Higheſt Court. Surely it was never queſtioned by ſober men ſince man was upon the face of the earth, till now; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the two (conſidering what an Image it is) had better warrant, the cunning Carver to faſhion the <hi>noſe</hi> by <hi>day;</hi> or the Carvers adverſarie, to ſtrip it off by <hi>night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That this Croſſe ſo defaced is not to be pittied, pitty ſhewen to ſtockes and ſtones argueth <hi>crueltie</hi> towards a
<hi>brother. A Righteous man regardeth the life of his beaſt; but the tender mercies of the wicked are</hi> (the tender mercies of the)
<hi>cruell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 12.10.</note> So we ſhould read it;
<hi>tender mercies,</hi> and cruell! that cannot bee: the meaning is, the
<hi>wicked have no mercies at all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plane nullae Jun.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Croſſe ſtands not by warrant of Law; but by the pleaſure of Man, holding only by <hi>Tenure</hi> of free will and ignorance.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That it is an Idol and muſt down; his <hi>covering</hi> and <hi>ornament</hi> muſt be <hi>defiled</hi> alſo, with the <hi>hand</hi> and <hi>heart</hi> both; &amp; this will cauſe wars, even the ſtrength of battle; for the heart will ſtruggle to maintaine his Idol, and the Idol will have great wrath, becauſe he <hi>knoweth that he hath but a ſhort time.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12.12.</note> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the trouble, God will overcome at laſt, and the Idol ſhall be defiled. But good proviſion is made, that the Citie, parting with an Idoll, may have an
<hi>Ornament,</hi> ſuch as will advance the name of her God, and be to the heart of the righteous there, the moſt ſpecious <hi>Ornament,</hi> that ever was ſeene in the world; A <hi>pillar</hi> ſhall be rayſed,
<hi>named, dedicated,</hi> to the Known God, <hi>known by confounding</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:112349:4"/> 
               <hi>His adverſaries, and working ſalvations</hi> for his <hi>Iſrael.</hi> An objection followes touching the Croſſe, and an anſwer thereunto, then a little good counſell, and then I have done prefacing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It will be ſaid, the Croſſe ſtands defaced onely and no more; it is not defiled: And perhaps his friends will beautifie him againe (they make him a god, againſt proprietie of ſpeech, it ſhall be the maſculine gender) waſh his face and wipe the duſt from his eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Perhaps ſo, yet I cannot beleeve it: Not, that now God has begun, His enemies ſhall make an end. The Croſſes caſe is before a judge, who will doe right, for He is the judge of all the world. He hath given ſentence in this caſe; But yet betwixt the giving ſentence againſt an evill work, and the execution of the ſame, there may lie, though no <hi>gulfe,</hi> yet a great ſpace of time: <hi>Therefore the hearts of the ſons of men are fully ſet in them to doe evill</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.11.</note>. while we are let <hi>alone</hi> (not troubled) wee are the more nearely <hi>joyned to Idolls</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.14</note>. But this is the comfort, ſentence is not onely pronounced, but in part executed upon theſe Idols: God hath appeared to be as He hath ſaid, <hi>I will be terrible to them, I will famiſh all the gods of the earth</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Zeph. 2.11.</note>. So He hath ſaid, then He wil do it, no doubt of that. He hath begun, Hee will make an end. Hee hath ſmitten the earth more <hi>terribly</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eſa. 2.19.</note> this laſt yeare, then the yeare before; It is not his manner (for his charge is againſt it) to ſmite like a man,
<hi>thrice</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2 King. 13.18.</note>, and then ſtay; Hee will go on till Hee Hath conſumed.</p>
            <p>But Reader, let us come home to our ſelves and conſider,
<hi>what patience have we?</hi> There is need of a great deale, and that it hath a <hi>perfect worke</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">James 1.4,</note>. Nay, there is a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Grace, get that, and we have all; <hi>What faith have we?</hi> you will ſay, a <hi>little faith, as a graine of Muſtardſeed.</hi> God be thanked for that <hi>little,</hi> for that will grow; But we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtay the growth of it. It was well anſwered to one, who ſaid he <hi>was getting ſuch a grace;</hi>
               <q rend="inline">"you ſhould have
<pb facs="tcp:112349:5"/> got it before, for you muſt uſe it now.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </q> We cannot live upon a
<hi>little</hi> in theſe <hi>deare, hard</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 8.28.</note>, <hi>and perilous</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>times.</hi> A little will not ſerve the turne now. Theſe are <hi>ſmiting</hi> &amp; extraordinary times. <hi>Take we unto us the whole Armour of God: above all taking</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ephe. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>the ſhield of faith.</hi> And now, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our ſelves ſtanding in a good poſture, like complea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſouldiers, having our <hi>militia</hi> well ordered and ſure, let us fall a <hi>ſmiting</hi> too; and ſo if the expreſſion be fit) ſave God the labour of <hi>ſmiting:</hi> when He ſmites, the ſtroke will be terrible. Either God muſt ſmite or we muſt ſmite. At what? Every man at the Idols in his own heart; There they are ſet up in that throne, elſe there had never been a ſtumbling blocke ſet up before the eye. We muſt <hi>ſmite</hi> at theſe; And we muſt ſmite, not as once the King did, by halves: he ſmote <hi>thrice</hi> and ſtayed. No, wee muſt ſmite five or ſix times, till we have ſmitten the Idols ſet up in our hearts, and have conſumed them; and then the ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks before the eyes will fall off themſelves and be utterly deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>We, ſilly men, can be taken with no argument but what may be felt. Behold here it is, and was intimated before. Look we all over the
<hi>circumference,</hi> and round about, and to every part of the ſame, ſo wide and large, we ſhall ſee all the lines of our ſorrowes, our troubles and our feares tend directly to the <hi>Idol</hi> in the heart, there they be
<hi>cente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> thence they come, be we well aware of it; That wee keepe our hearts with all dilligence, and our ſoules from Idols. Then ſee the benefit; though we have the bread of affliction for our meate here, and teares in plenty for our drinke (for in reforming times ſo it may fall out) yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all that, it will be <hi>peace at the laſt:</hi> There is a word of promiſe for that; though at <hi>evening tide trouble,</hi> yet in
<hi>the morning it is not</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Eſa. 17.14.</note>: Though in the middeſt of our yeares, &amp; for a moment afterwards we are diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted; yet, doing as a foreſaid, <hi>our end ſhall be peace.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112349:5"/>
            <head>THE CROSSES CASE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Caſe opened. The injury done to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers worke there. His blaſphemy in giving ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Names to that, which his owne fingers have made.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſad Story touching the <hi>Croſſe</hi> begins, which yet made ſober men laugh, others cry, or doe worſe. Not long ſince a notable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity was done upon the <hi>Pile</hi> of <hi>Images</hi> in Cheape-ſide of ancient ſtanding there. Some body, we are ſure of that, and a Man ſure, but whether one or two or more, we cannot ſo well tell, ſtept up above the barres of Iron there incloſing the Croſſe, wrencht off a <hi>Leg</hi> and part of the <hi>Thigh</hi> from that <hi>Image,</hi> they preſumptuouſly called <hi>Chriſt;</hi> pluckt away the <hi>Popes Miter; diſarmed</hi> his <hi>Cardinall;</hi> crackt the <hi>Queene</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112349:6"/> 
                  <hi>Mothers Crowne,</hi> tooke away the halfe, and moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully defaced a fift, for its <hi>Noſe</hi> is gone.</p>
               <p>In common ſpeech we call theſe Images ſo, as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull Painter, drawing the figure of a <hi>Lion,</hi> and ſuppoſing the beholders might thinke it an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> he writ at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Table, <hi>This is a Lyon.</hi> Well then becauſe theſe Images ſtand upright like the <hi>Palme,</hi> wee will take them to be as they are called, neither <hi>Beares,</hi> nor <hi>Lions,</hi> but as in vulgar opinion and common ſpeech; the firſt I dare not Name, the ſecond the <hi>Pope,</hi> the third his Cardinall, the fourth the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> the fift I know not who, old Saint <hi>George</hi> perhaps, Doctor <hi>Heylins</hi> Saint; or Saint <hi>Innocent,</hi> for it ſtands like an harmeleſſe fellow, more like to take a wrong then to doe any; but if it be hee, he has beene a brave fellow, a <hi>Pope</hi> in his dayes, ſome ſay a <hi>Biſhop</hi> now; or Saint <hi>Faux;</hi> he had that honour conferred upon him ever ſince his Fire-worke.</p>
               <p>Reader, let us underſtand our owne freedome, that wee have as great a libertie of conceit in theſe caſes as the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hath, and may uſe the ſame libertie in giving a Name to this Saint now its
<hi>Noſe</hi> is off, as the Carver did when hee firſt put the
<hi>Noſe</hi> on. And we will give it a true Name, the ſame which all its Anceſtors have had before it: As the plaine fellow ſaid, hee would call a
<hi>Spade a Spade,</hi> that hee would, and ſo we are reſolved to doe; or, which more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtucteth, as the good King called the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> in thoſe dayes, when they would burne incenſe to it, not the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> then, but <hi>Nehuſhtan</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">2 King.
18.4.</note> plaine braſſe and no more, nor of any more uſe then; ſo wee muſt call it (and there is much more reaſon for it)
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>Stone;</hi> ſome more coſt and paines beſtowed upon it and its fellowes by the Carver, then what they had when they lay together in the ſame <hi>Quarrey,</hi> and yet but a
<hi>Stone.</hi> And it is the Name by which the <hi>Lord</hi> calls them;
<hi>She defiled the land and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Adultery;</hi> with what? with
<hi>Stones</hi> and with <hi>Stockes.</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Jer.
3.9.</note> The cunning Carver ſhould well obſerve this, who, as bold now as ever, dares give different Names to <hi>Similar</hi> or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112349:6"/> like parts, as that this <hi>Stone</hi> is, I muſt adde, &amp;c. for I feare to ſpeake forth; but this I will ſay, a
<hi>lie</hi> is in his mouth, as it is in his hand, and blaſphemy alſo. All his Art and Coſt can make it no other thing, but what it is, <hi>Wood</hi> and <hi>Stone;</hi> therefore <hi>the part</hi> (of the wood and ſtone)
<hi>Muſt have the ſame Name with the whole.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pars ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milaris eſt, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> idem cum toto Nomen ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.</hi>
                  </note> But it cannot be expected that the cunning workeman will heare and feare and doe no more preſumptuouſly, becauſe it hath beene a queſtion long ſince,
<hi>whether the Carver or his ſtocke bee more ſenſeleſſe.</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 135.18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Having now given this Saint its true Name, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to all its fellowes, being deſcended from the ſame <hi>common ſtocke,</hi> and having reproved the <hi>Carvers</hi> blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, I goe on in my ſtory to enquire the time when this <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge</hi> (as they call it) was committed. VVhen was it done? VVe cannot tell the preciſe time; it was a Night worke, that is certaine; for, as was ſaid touching the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing of ſuch another Image; <hi>And ſo it was becauſe he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his fathers houſehould, and the Men of the Citie that hee could not doe it by day, that he did it by Night.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 6.27.</note> So here, the Man (for I will take him ſingle) feared the Men of the Citie, and did it by Night; what time of the night? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the third or fourth watch is uncertaine too. But certaine it is he watcht his time, and tooke it whilſt the Watch was faſt aſleepe. So we have the ſtory: now heare what followed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The next morning opened the caſe more clearely, and the thoughts of men about it. Next night they made their <hi>watch</hi> ſtrong, but had they thought on it ſooner, they had made a wiſer choyce. Ancient Records aſſure us, that <hi>Geeſe</hi> are the moſt approved
<hi>watch,</hi> and choiſeſt <hi>guard</hi> about Images.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NExt morning the <hi>battery</hi> made upon the Croſſe was in the paſſengers eye; they came thither after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112349:7"/> to make ſupplication; and, beholding what was done, in ſtead of ſupplication they put up a rayling accuſation againſt him, that had done them no hurt: And the wiſe Citizens, neighbours there abouts, were troubled about it, they chattered, and little better then railed too. Then they reſolved upon the queſtion (for they ſaw they had to doe with a <hi>ſleeping watch</hi>) to watch it better for after times, ſo to keepe their Croſſe in a <hi>poſture</hi> of defence: for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they had <hi>Souldiers</hi> keeping watch about it, and a
<hi>Captaine</hi> a good friend to the ſame. Had they but one night ſooner taken their time for ſo grave a conſultation, and beene pleaſed to have admitted me into their councell, I thinke I ſhould have over-ruled them by a ruled caſe, and ſo have diſwaded from making choyce of Souldiers to watch their Croſſe: for they for the moſt part, and as their ſupply is, will eate and drinke to the full, and then, as experience tells us, are faſt aſleepe when the ſpoyler comes. The Children of darkneſſe were wiſer at this point, then are they, who profeſſe themſelves children of light. They committed the ſafeguard of their Images to thoſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which are very wakefull, being fed with dry meate, and their drinke is as ſmall as water. It is a <hi>Booke-Caſe</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in the Romane Antiquities, and thereon depends a very bloody ſtory; I will paſſe that over, and briefely ſet downe ſo much as relates to the caſe, becauſe it may ſtand us in ſtead, if not to <hi>watch</hi> the Croſſe, yet to ſafeguard our houſes.</p>
               <p>The Romans had a <hi>plurality</hi> of <hi>Images</hi> as wee have
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> (I muſt not yet call them <hi>Gods</hi> nor
<hi>Idols</hi> neither, I ſhall anon by very good warrant) their
<hi>Houſhold</hi> and their <hi>Cloſſet</hi> Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; ſome ſtanding more open, other ſome more reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But theſe ſuffered many indignities and very ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full uſage, not onely from Mice, Rats, and Spiders, but from the hands of violent Men, who have tumbled them about the houſe, and trod them like mire in the ſtreet, as if the Carver had beſtowed no coſt nor worth upon them.</p>
               <p>They had alſo their <hi>Tutelar</hi> Images, ſuch wherein they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112349:7"/> placed the ſafeguard of their Citie, and whereto they gave the ſame <hi>Veneration,</hi> (I muſt not ſay
<hi>Adoration</hi>) as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to their Croſſe; theſe they committed to their ſtrongeſt hold, their Capitoll; and for their ſafeguard and ſureſt <hi>watch,</hi> there they appointed a moſt wakefull <hi>Guard</hi> over them, a <hi>guard</hi> of <hi>Geeſe,</hi> which did diſcharge their <hi>cure</hi> very well and like themſelves, and ſo quitted the place in a time of great extremity and moſt eminent danger, as wee may reade if we would draw out the ſtory a little longer. I will record no more of the ſtory here, but what <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie</hi> was done by the <hi>Romans</hi> to their <hi>Geeſe</hi> for their good ſervice done to them and their Images; in memory where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and in returne of thankefulneſſe for ſuch a deliverance; The <hi>Romans</hi> appointed as great a <hi>Feſtivall</hi> to the honour of their <hi>Geeſe,</hi> as the Papiſts doe to the glory of their Croſſe, for it ſtands upon record at this day, being regiſtred the <hi>Gooſes Holiday.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Luc Fl. lib.</hi>
1. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Aug. de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi>
22.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>All that hath beene ſaid hitherto was intended purpoſely for the ſcorne of Images, their Carvers, Servers, and upholders. The Sober man can turne to a ſacred <hi>Story,</hi> and learne from it the doome of Images, and Image ſervers.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT will be ſaid now, <hi>That all this hitherto is ridiculous.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is ſo acknowledged, and ſo intended, as beſt befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting now the brutiſh workeman and his worke; The Name he preſumptuouſly puts upon it; the regard alſo and <hi>watch</hi> he fooliſhly ſets about it: Hee that will be ſerious, can turn to the ſacred ſtory, thence obſerve a greater <hi>defilement</hi> then was all this here with us, upon the Images and their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, for there was a
<hi>Guard</hi> and <hi>Captaine</hi> ſet about them, <hi>who ſmote the worſhippers with the edge of the Sword,</hi> then brought <hi>forth the Images and burnt them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 10.23.25,26.</note> They ceaſed not here, for they brake downe the very chiefe and <hi>Prince</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:112349:8"/> of the Images (the <hi>Image</hi> of
<hi>Baal</hi>)
<note place="margin">Verſ. 27.</note> and <hi>they brake downe its houſe over its head,</hi> and about its eares too. VVhat then? then
<hi>Baals</hi> friends called a guard to watch it by night, and cunning workemen to build it by day; and Carvers to forme and faſhion it anew; was it not ſo? No, <hi>Baal</hi> had not a friend that durſt appeare for him. I pray you let us reade on in the ſtory, and obſerve it well; The Souldiers and Captaines brake downe the houſe, (the covering of <hi>Baal,</hi> that which ſheltered it from the injury of weather, wee ſhall heare more of that anon) and made it <hi>a draught houſe unto this day.</hi> Here was a defilement indeed, a notable indignitie, greater by farre then had been, if they had pluckt off his Legge and Thigh too, and Noſe alſo; they ſhattered the <hi>Image</hi> to peeces; they brake downe the houſe of
<hi>Baal;</hi> and which was the higheſt indignitie that could be offered, but beſt befitting that Lordly thing, they ſet there in place and ſtead thereof, a <hi>veſſell, wherein is no pleaſure,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſea 8.8.</note> for they made <hi>Baals</hi> houſe a
<hi>Draught-houſe unto this day;</hi> Now <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> friends will appeare in his caſe, and object here, Firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ob.</hi>
                  </note>That theſe
<hi>worſhippers ſo ſmote with the edge of the Sword</hi> were the worſhippers of <hi>Baal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>An.</hi>
                  </note>Yes there is no doubt of that, for the context is plaine:
<note n="b" place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> but yet this is more then they will grant us anon; when they will ſay, it is one thing to
<hi>ſerve</hi> an Image, another thing to <hi>worſhip</hi> it (but of this in due place.) Theſe worſhipped <hi>Baal,</hi> that is plaine, and were called <hi>Baalites,</hi> ſuch, who cut and ſlaſhed themſelves till the blood guſhed forth upon them, much after the manner as the Papiſts uſe upon their <hi>Good Friday.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 18.28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> 2.</note>And the Image was
<hi>Baals Image;</hi> and then it was ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved well enough, for it was an
<hi>Idol,</hi> and the moſt filthy, beaſtly, moſt abominable
<hi>Idol</hi> that ever was gazed upon; ſome conclude the name of it was
<hi>Priapus,</hi> and there is ſcarce any man, Scholler or no Scholler, but he knowes what that was, a ſilthy god indeed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>An.</hi> 2.</note>My little reading can give little ſatisfaction what this Idols Name was; <hi>Baal</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> is a common Name as <hi>Lord</hi> with us;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112349:8"/> and hee was reſembled by divers
<hi>figures</hi> according to the pleaſure of the Carver and the imployment he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned unto: He ſerved the <hi>Sechemites</hi> according to
<hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> as their <hi>Guardian</hi> or <hi>Tutelar</hi> god, which they called <hi>Baal-Berith,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Jud. 8 33</note> and his <hi>Figure</hi> was (I conjecture ſo, and the wiſeſt can no more) a
<hi>Gooſe.</hi> He ſerved others to drive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <hi>flies,</hi> which they called <hi>Baal-Zebub,</hi> their <hi>Fly-god:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 1.3. <hi>vid. junium.</hi>
                  </note> and his figure was a <hi>flye.</hi> He ſerved others to watch their fields, and gardens to fright away the Crowes thence, which they called <hi>Baal-peor,</hi> and his figure was,
<hi>Priapus</hi> as ſome <hi>affirme</hi> at this day. Theſe are but conjectures wherein we take a latitude: The truth is, <hi>Baals</hi> Image was a very <hi>proteus</hi> for his various ſhapes; he was every thing, what the Carver pleaſed, and yet <hi>nothing,</hi> neither fiſh nor fleſh; but if any thing in the world then <hi>wood</hi> or <hi>ſtone,</hi> a very ſtock, which is the Name was given to all his Anceſtors, and muſt ſerve to all the pedegree of Images unto the worlds end. The holy Ghoſt gives us his proper Name, calling him, <hi>That ſhame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">d Hoſea
9.10.</note> We are ſure that is his Name, and belongs of right to all
<hi>the ſtocke of Images</hi> that ever were, or ever ſhall be framed by the cunning Workemen, not a <hi>ſhamefull</hi> Idoll, but in the
<hi>Abſtract, That ſhame.</hi> And yet let us take good notice of this, that <hi>Baals</hi> Image, <hi>that ſhame,</hi> was not ſuch a
<hi>ſhame,</hi> ſuch a filthy thing as is that <hi>Image</hi> ſo lately defiled. VVhy ſo? Becauſe <hi>Baals</hi> Image was, as it was named,
<hi>Baals Image;</hi> and this had its forme or figure as you heard, a
<hi>Gooſe,</hi> a <hi>Flye,</hi> or a loathſome thing, which I will name no more, being called by his proper Name, and ſo it was named, <hi>that ſhame;</hi> like to like, a very good agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But the Image now ſo lately defiled is as filthy all over as <hi>Baals</hi> Image was: and that which makes it more filthy and more abominable yet, is the Name, the daring workeman at firſt put upon it, was received from his mouth and ſo continued to this day, he named it and ſo do others from his mouth; (I feare to ſpeake after them, yet I muſt) <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Lord Chriſt declaring himſelfe to be the Sonne of God with <hi>power by the reſurrection from the dead</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 1.4.</note> All this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112349:9"/> ſuggeſted in the Name, for they call the Image now defiled <hi>Chriſt riſing from the grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truely I want words to ſet forth the abominations and Blaſphemies of this generation, I meane the generation of thoſe cunning vile men, thoſe Image-Carvers. And ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, now I remember, words could ſtand us in no ſtead, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the workemen and their workes are alike, ſo blockiſh, and ſenſeleſſe, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>VVe will conclude from the premiſſes, that, ſith this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage is ſo filthy and abominable, yet is called by ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a name: Sith, it is <hi>that ſhame,</hi> that <hi>ſhame</hi> to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to profeſſion, to the Goſpell, to thoſe who would <hi>ſhew themſelves Men,</hi> and yet is Named <hi>that glory,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of the
<hi>Church</hi> her <hi>Chriſt,</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and a <hi>Prieſt;</hi> ſith I ſay it is ſo named, and yet this
<hi>Glory</hi> is changed into the ſimilitude of a <hi>Stone</hi> or
<hi>Lead,</hi> ſuch vile and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter; therefore the perſon that pluckt off the <hi>Leaden</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g and part of the Thigh from the Image did very well: And if the Magiſtrate now ſhall breake downe all the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and defile their Covering, ſo <hi>deſtroying them out of Iſrael,</hi> he ſhall doe better: for beſides what hath beene ſaid, we muſt conſider this, That
<hi>Baals</hi> Image, though a filthy thing, <hi>that ſhame,</hi> yet was the Image (as ours are) ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſant to the eyes, and to be deſired; which appeares, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a wiſe and underſtanding people were inamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with it, ſo as they joyned
<hi>themſelves to it.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Numb. 25.3.</note> See how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring theſe filthy things were! They were a trap and a ſnare and a ginne to Gods owne people. Are they not as inſnaring ſtill? I will inquire into that anon, and reſolve it. In the meane time ſober men will learne by this, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their charge and doe thereafter; <hi>Yee ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all defile alſo the covering of thy graven Images of Silver, and the Ornament of thy molten Images of Gold; thou ſhalt caſt them away as a menſtruous cloth, thou ſhalt ſay unto it, get thee hence.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>VVe ſhall make very good uſe of this ſacred Scripture anon, in defence of the accuſed if he ſtood at the barre: In the meane time we will take a view of what is ſaid; The <hi>mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of theſe men is rebuked, who miſcall their Images; their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112349:9"/> folly manifeſt for keeping a guard and watch over them: ſober men have taken forth their leſſon alſo. Now I muſt reprove theſe ſo pittifull men for ſhewing mercy and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly compaſſion towards ſtockes and ſtones. Surely a <hi>ſcorne</hi> will be put upon them for ſuch fooliſh pitty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Their fooliſh pitty is laughed at by the Ancients, Jewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; Living Images command pitty, the dead ſcorne.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Will not aske the former ſort (the Papiſts) <hi>what ayleth them</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Iudg. 18.24.</note>, for their gods are defaced. Nor will I at preſent ſay to the other ſort, as he to the men that ſtood by, will <hi>yee plead for Baal, will yee ſave him</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Iudg. 6.31. <hi>Barn.</hi> 6. <hi>Hor. Sect.</hi> 1.
<hi>Sect.</hi> 8. <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. <hi>Ep.</hi> 39. <hi>Tib.</hi> 1.10. <hi>M. faelix in fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 16.
<hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>v d. Com. Lact.</hi> 2.2.</note>? I thinke it may fit very well to reaſon out the caſe a little in ſcorne of that Image, as I find both Jewes and Gentiles, Heathens and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have done before me in the like caſe; and ſo I ſhall make way to my ſcope after this manner; Here is a battery committed; What though? let him complaine that is <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, hurt,</hi> or <hi>grieved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, here is no dammage none at all; the <hi>Popes</hi> power is not a jot the leſſe now his <hi>Miter</hi> is gone; his Cardinall can do as much with one hand, as he did before with two. And the
<hi>Mother</hi> can command her <hi>ſonne</hi> as <hi>imperiouſly</hi> as ever ſhe did, though halfe her crowne be gone. And the defaced Saint ſmels as well now without a <hi>Noſe</hi> as before when it was freſh and new out of the Carvers ſhop. They have received no dammage none at all.</p>
               <p>Secondly, nor are they hurt or grieved; It is their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence you will ſay to ſtand ſtocke ſtill and ſilent, when vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied or injured: yes, be it ſo, but here I ſhould rather thinke it the effect of
<hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>cuſtome:</hi> for theſe Images have beene ſo long expoſed to the ſcattering of Crowes and other birds, to the ſpitting and ſpauling, to the injury of weather, haile, raine, windes; that now they can ſuffer any thing, even duſt to be caſt into their eyes, and yet not wipe it off. Here
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112349:10"/> is no hurt done, no grievance at all. The Image next cryed not <hi>Oh,</hi> no not when the fellow pluckt off its legge and thigh both; nor did it reſiſt at all, nor thruſt the man from it, when he more then played with its noſe; doubtleſſe there was no hurt done, for then it would have cryed out in the eares of its neighbours. Why then doe the men of the City complaine? where lieth the griefe? they are a little wiſer I hope then <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver Smith, and pretty well perſwaded <hi>That they are no Gods which are made with hands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 19.26.</note> why then ſhould they complaine as they doe and call out ſo bitterly?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Theſe ſo pittifull men ſhew compaſſion to the Croſſe and none to the Citie; they are queſtioned and rebuked for ſo doing.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THey have but one thing to anſwer, and truely they will ſpeake againſt their owne Soules; they tell us a goodly pile of Images is defaced, which (they will tell us anon) they accounted an ornament to the place.</p>
               <p>VVell but ſith they will cry out of this indignitie, which was offered to a pile of ſtones; I muſt queſtion them about their outcry in the preſence of God, &amp; they muſt anſwer as in the ſame preſence. But who are they that are now to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned? if they are not knowne by their contrary walking; nor their folly yet made manifeſt, it ſhall not be made ſo by my pen. The dutie of private perſons is to go backward and cover the nakedneſſe of their brethren; and in reference thereto, I hope my care ſhall be to carry all levell to this marke, <hi>the good of my brother and his information;</hi> therefore I muſt queſtion them for their fooliſh pitty (indeed you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give it a lighter word.) But before I queſtion them I muſt put downe a <hi>Theſis</hi> firſt, a truth which no man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and it is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">"Man, as he is the moſt excellent creature in the world ſo is he the moſt noble and venerable <hi>Image</hi> that ever was looked upon ſince <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was upon the earth; he is a living Image of God, made by the very hand of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112349:10"/> God, and in this reſpect a thouſand fold more excellent then all Images made by the hand of Man; this is the
<hi>Theſis;</hi> I muſt premiſe three words more.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Six yeares agoe or thereabouts, three Images were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed all at once, which could breath, and ſmell, and heare, and wipe the duſt from their eyes; yea, ſuch they were, that had knowledge to open the eyes of them, who were borne blind. Theſe three were Pillored, defaced, ſtigmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, in plaine Engliſh, markt for Rogues, becauſe they were faithfull and kept cloſe to the Law of their God, as was made manifeſt when their cauſe was made knowne, and the VVord of the Lord had tryed them; we reade on there,
<hi>Then they ſent and looſed them, the Peeres and the people, let them goe free.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.18,19,20.</note> But when time was, ſo villainouſly they were uſed, and for the reaſon above ſaid.</p>
               <p>Now I put the queſtion to theſe pittifull men, much after the ſame, which <hi>Gidion</hi> put to <hi>Zeba</hi> and
<hi>Zalmunna;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 8.18</note> 
                  <hi>What manner of Images were they, which yee ſaw (or heard were) ſo abuſed?</hi> They muſt anſwer as their brethren in that place did, <hi>As thou art ſo were they, each one reſembled the Children of a King.</hi> Then I muſt reply as followeth, <hi>They were your brethren even the ſonnes of your mother.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> I may goe on, for the caſe will allow of the ſame zeale; <hi>As the Lord liveth</hi> the pitty and compaſſion theſe men have ſhewen to ſtockes and ſtones when they ſhewed none to their owne fleſh, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for vengeance againſt them. VVhat? can they pitty Images, which cannot wipe the duſt from their eyes, and can they ſhew no pitty at all to theſe, who reſemble the children of a King, who are their Brethren, even the Sons of their Mother? As the Lord liveth they have done and ſpoken all this for and behalfe of the Croſſe againſt their owne ſoules. VVhat? ſo carefull to maintaine the hononr of their Croſſe, and ſo careleſſe of their brethren? <hi>That that dyeth let it die, and that that is to be cut off let it be cut off.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zech. 11.9.</note> VVhat care they? (I allude to theſe words, which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the words of the Lord, ſhewing Himſelfe careleſſe of a ſtubborne people, who would be careleſſe of Him, and of His words) what ſo careleſſe of their Brethren? <hi>David</hi> was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112349:11"/> not ſo towards his enemies;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.13.14.</note>
                  <hi>But as for me when they were ſicke my cloathing was ſackcloath; I humbled my ſoule with faſting, I behaved my ſelfe as though he had beene my friend or Brother; I bowed downe heavily as one that mourneth for his Mother.</hi> It is a point of humanitie to pitty men in their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie; it may be our owne caſe, being our <hi>ſelves alſo in the body;</hi> I aske againe, what, ſo careleſſe of their Brethren? why not as careleſſe of ſtockes and ſtones?<note place="margin">Heb. 13 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord ſmote <hi>Jonahs Gourd,</hi> and it withered, He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared alſo a vehement wind, which with the Sunne beate upon the head of
<hi>Ionah,</hi> that he fainted, and then he ſpake like a diſtempered Man, unadviſedly with his lippes. VVee muſt obſerve how the Lord queſtions him. <hi>Doſt thou well to be angry for the Gourd Ionah?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ionah 4.8.</note> Yes; Then ſaid the Lord, <hi>Thou haſt had pitty on the Gourd, for the which thou haſt not loboured, neither madeſt it grow, why then is thy eye evill?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> wherefore art thou diſpleaſed, that I ſhould ſpare ſo great a Citty, where are ſo many perſons and ſo much Cattle? This reproofe would fall heavy upon theſe men, for they have pittied a more baſe, vile, and contemptible thing then was the Gourd; but they have not pittied their Brethren, nor that place, where are ſo many perſons and ſo much Cattle; I doe preſent it onely to their ſaddeſt and moſt retired thoughts, and conclude it with a yet ſharper reproofe from the Lords owne Mouth in a very like caſe, for then they did <hi>laviſh gold out of a bag</hi> to beautifie an Image; here they have done as much and more, for they <hi>laviſh</hi> words al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to defend the ſame; The reproofe is, and it is a ſharpe one;
<hi>Remember this, and ſhew your ſelves Men; bring it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to mind O ye tranſgreſſours.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 46.8.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112349:11"/>
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>They juſtifie themſelves with a little Reaſon, and as little Law, which tells them, That their brethren were defaced by power from lawfull authoritie; the Croſſe not ſo, but in an unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted way. The contrary is maintained, and the perſon
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the beſt reaſon and Law both, and in the Higheſt Court, the Law and Court of Heaven.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>VVE muſt heare now what theſe wiſe Men have to ſay for themſelves, for they will not be mad with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reaſon. They have a twofold Reaſon, and the latter hath ſome ſhew of Law, why they were ſo careleſſe of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and have enveighed ſo much againſt the defilement of, and injurious dealing (as they call it) againſt their Croſſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they doe acknowledge as Men, that a <hi>friend indeed loveth at all times, and a brother is borne for adverſitie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 17.17.</note> Nay they yeeld too; <hi>That there is a friend that ſticketh cloſer then a Brother.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov.
18.24.</note> But yet in that they ſhewed themſelves neither as friends nor as Brothers to their Brethren in adverſitie, they have this onely to ſay,
<hi>That better is a neighbour that is neare, then a Brother that is afar off.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 21.10.</note> Therein is the pith of their Reaſon. The Croſſe is their Neighbour neere unto them, daily in their eye, which falling into the hands of a theefe who wounded it, commands their pitty: their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are afar off, ſome beyond the Seas, all out of ſight, and then out of mind, and not regarded: So they ſay, or if they ſay not ſo, yet their actions make their thoughts and words legible.</p>
               <p>I would onely adviſe here, that they would turne to the parable, and reſolve themſelves at this point, Who is their Neighbour?<note place="margin">Luk. 10.29.</note> The Croſſe they ſay; The fore-quoated place tells them no, their Brother is their neighbour; and their neighbour their brother all the world over. He that is fallen into the hands of ſpoylers; He that needs my hand or my heart, my purſe or my prayers, he is my neighbour, though a thouſand miles off from me.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:112349:12"/> I ſay againe, he is neighbour and brother too. VVho? Not that, which is neareſt to me in place, for ſo ſtockes and ſtones may be, as in this caſe. But he who pertakes of the ſame common nature with me, and ſo chalengeth a neare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with my affections and place in my heart; hee is my neighbour. The neighbour-hood then (for ſo we may call it) of the Croſſe ſhould not have taken up any roome in their thoughts, <hi>living Images</hi> were ſpoyled and left wounded; they ſtood bound to ſhew themſelves neighbours; to ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy what they could; But cleane contrary they neglected their brethren and ſhewed themſelves neighbours unto dead Images, for there they ſhewed mercy, and would not be accounted uncharitable men for all that, for they have now a ſecond Reaſon which they call Law.</p>
               <p>2. What was done to theſe <hi>living Images</hi> was done by the hand of lawfull power. So they ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>I cannot yeeld that. A
<hi>power</hi> it was, permitted by <hi>God,</hi> but maintayn'd againſt
<hi>God</hi> and His lawes, and the undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Right of His ſubjects and people; but that diſpute is needleſſe here, let it paſſe. Grant them their ſaying, let the <hi>Authority</hi> be whoſe it will be (the Devills I thinke, for hee doth caſt the Righteous into priſon)
<note place="margin">Revel. 2.10.</note> yet will it not follow, that they ſhould not ſhew pitty and compaſſion to their Brethren, children of a King, and ſonnes of the ſame Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: they goe on reaſoning and object.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obj.</hi>
                  </note>This inſolent fellow committed a Riot, and made a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery upon a venerable Image againſt all Reaſon, and in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to Authoritie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>VVe will examine that, and muſt reply. The man did not act againſt Reaſon; knowledge and underſtanding guided his ſteps, carrying him to that worke, the defiling of thoſe Images: For it was concluded long ſince from the Chayre at Oxford;
<hi>That it was expedient the Croſſe ſhould be taken away:</hi> ſurely there was Reaſon and reading both, and this the Man might know being ſo publikely knowne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obj.</hi>
                  </note>They reply; It was not concluded from the Chaire that Common hands ſhould remove or defile it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>VVhy may not common hands ſerve to remove an uncleane
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112349:12"/> thing. It is an uncleane thing; and
<hi>common</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane</hi> will ſtand together. But this is to begge the Queſtion, which we are to reſolve anon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obj.</hi>
                  </note>Their meaning is; It is not concluded that a man ſhould doe this without, or againſt the command of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; things muſt be done orderly, by order from lawfull Authority.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>True, and ſo he did; not without, or againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the <hi>Ruler,</hi> the King of kings, and Lord of lords. The command is peremptory, directed not to one but to the people;
<note place="margin">Deut. 12.23.</note>
                  <hi>And you ſhall overthrow their Altars, and breake their Pillars, and burne their groves with fire, and you ſhall bow downe the graven Images of their Gods; and deſtroy the Names of them out of that place;</hi> Marke how the charge runnes, like a VVhirle-wind, for it is againſt Images; <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, hew, breake downe, deſtroy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obj.</hi>
                  </note>But it is meant you ſhall doe this, but not againſt the mind of the Ruler.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>I anſwer firſt: when we have a command from above, no command from below can counter-checke it: His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand who is abſolute muſt ſtand; according to His charge things muſt be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obj.</hi>
                  </note>But in an orderly way, not with tumults and noyſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  </note>Here was neither: he did his worke neither with <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> nor with <hi>tumultk.</hi> The noyſe and tumult was the next morning and after night by thoſe who maintained the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> of the Croſſe.<note place="margin">Act.
24.18</note>
               </p>
               <p>VVe abhorre tumultuary courſes, heady and unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able proceedings, and have nothing whereof to accuſe the <hi>Croſſes enemies</hi> herein: That which he or they did againſt it, was done, as was now ſaid, not with tumult or noyſe, but with as much diſcretion and ſilence as could be. The Croſſes friends they came with <hi>multitu de</hi> and with <hi>tumult;</hi> with a Guard and a Captaine both, againſt all <hi>preſidents</hi> of former Ages, except in the caſe of <hi>Baals Altar,</hi> They ſhould have reſolved as <hi>Jehu</hi> (in the like caſe) and ſaid as he did;<note place="margin">2 King. 10.18.</note> the perſon yeſternight <hi>ſerved Baal a little,</hi> wee ſhall ſerve <hi>him much;</hi> he tooke away the legge and thigh we will take
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112349:13"/> away the whole bulke, he pluckt off the
<hi>Noſe,</hi> we will plucke of its head. This had beene a worke for a Guard and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and but according to former preſidents.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obj.</hi>
                  </note>But that which was done, and that which is argued ſhould have beene done, that and this muſt have a warrant from the Ruler, his <hi>Fiat</hi> firſt, let it be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>Indeed it ſhould have beene ſo, and then it had beene done more decently, and in better order.</p>
               <p>How much to be wiſhed, that ſo it might have beene, that the
<hi>Chiefe</hi> and Prime Man in the Citie had beene the firſt that would have <hi>conſecrated his hands upon the Image?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod.
32.29.</note> Then things are done decently, and in order to a bleſſing, when the Ruler like a true <hi>Gideon,</hi> goes before, and bids his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers <hi>looke on me and doe likewiſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg.
7.17</note> VVhat hopes the man had, that the Magiſtrate would leade him the way to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing of the Croſſe, I examine not, but leave the world to judge; certaine it is, the Man ſaw that nothing did ſo croſſe the
<hi>Militia</hi> of the kingdome as Croſſes, and Images (I muſt not call them Idolls yet) out-facing God and His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand there: Therefore he would venture upon the talleſt of them all, and hazard his joynts to plucke off a limbe, which the cunning Carver had put on. VVho hath any thing to ſay to that? His joynts are his owne, and well ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded in a matter ſo nearely concerning the honour of God. It was a <hi>Zeale according to knowledge</hi> for ought wee can ſee, and well ordered for ought I know, or any wiſe man dare judge. And it is to be thought according to the Rule of pure charitie and right reaſon, that he feares God and honours the <hi>Ruler</hi> as much and more then they that complaine of him, and ſtand ſo ſtiffe for the
<hi>Militia</hi> of the Croſſe. He waited patiently theſe ſeventeene yeares what the Magiſtrate would doe, and obſerving him this yeare more ready to beautifie the Croſſe then to defile it, and ſuch a fall of Idols, and Idoll-ſhepeheards, and yet the Croſſe ſtanding ſtill, he reſolved to venture a broken ſhin and to play the Souldier, ſo entred the
<hi>Liſts</hi> againſt <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Cardinall,</hi> and the venerable <hi>Lady</hi> too. And truely the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112349:13"/> was I thinke, beyond expectation, ſuch as may aſſure us, he had a power with him, a watch and guard over him, for he diſarmed the Adverſaries, returned conquerour, loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the ſpoyles of <hi>Miters, Armes, Noſes, Crownes,</hi> and ſo, by the benefit of the Night he got the day and is ſafe enough.</p>
               <p>Let them that are grieved complaine: It is a very ſmall thing to him who complaines againſt him in that matter; he thankes God, the <hi>Law is open,</hi> the law of Heaven he meanes, and the two bloody Courts are ſhut: He takes no more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie now then before, for he choſe the
<hi>Night</hi> to doe that, which ſhould have beene done in the <hi>Day time</hi> and before the <hi>Sunne:</hi> But he knowes, that which would have beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a crime there, is accounted a vertue now in the judgement of good men, and the Court of Heaven:
<note place="margin">* <hi>Quae hic mala putau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, hac ſunt in coelo bona Lact.</hi> 5.15. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1 Cor. 4.3.</note> and thereto he appeales and from thence he hath his <hi>Quetus eſt</hi> in this matter. And he is aſſured that when the Lord comes, Who will both bring to light the <hi>hidden things of darkneſſe, and will make manifeſt the Counſells of the hearts;</hi> hee ſhall have prayſe for defiling that which God Himſelfe, and the ſoules of all the Godly doe loath and abominate.</p>
               <p>And ſo much to cleare the perſon from the cavills of lewd men, who hold up dead Images and throw downe the living, what they can; pittying the one and neglecting the other. This could not be omitted here becauſe the folly of ſuch men muſt be made manifeſt, who made an outcry now when they ſhould have rejoyced; and complayned not, nor mourned when time was, though they were called unto both; for ſo <hi>David</hi> did, he mourned for his enemies, theſe not ſo for their Friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112349:14"/>
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Twenty Arguments to maintaine the Militia of the Croſſe, our men refuſe them all, create one of their owne; It muſt ſtand becauſe it is an <hi>Ornament.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe chiefe and hardeſt worke is now behind, and is like to cauſe a hot conteſtation. The queſtion is, <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this pile of Images ſhall ſtand or fall?</hi> The adverſary puts himſelfe in good hope, and the thing out of all queſtion; <hi>The Croſſe ſhall ſtand,</hi> for he hath twenty arguments for the ſtanding and maintayning of it in a <hi>poſture of defence.</hi> There is no Papiſt ſo ſilly and ſimple but if he can tell; and is ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of it, that twice ten is twenty, he hath ſo many Arguments for the Croſſe and the maintayning the <hi>Militia</hi> of the ſame. But I ſhall not trouble my ſelfe and the Reader with any one of thoſe Arguments, for juſt reaſons; Firſt, becauſe I am not to contend with rigid and profeſſed Papiſts. But with Proteſtants at large, and in Name onely and they will not urge any one of theſe arguments for the ſtanding of the Croſſe. (indeed they are aſhamed of them, they are ſo ridiculous.) Beſides, if I ſhall prove anon that the <hi>Croſſe</hi> is an
<hi>Idoll,</hi> as I thinke, I ſhall, then thoſe twentie Arguments and as many more will not be worth two ſtrawes, I doe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Reader that our <hi>Military</hi> men, I meane thoſe, that ſtand-for, defend, watch and ward the Croſſe, doc renounce all thoſe Arguments, twentie at the leaſt, thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wiſe enough to frame an Argument, that they may call their owne, which the Papiſts doe ſcorne alſo. If my word might be taken I would give it with the ſtrongeſt aſſurance that Man can give; that they have but one argument for the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Croſſe, I meane for the defence thereof, and that is this. <hi>It is an ornament to the place where it ſtands, and to the whole Citie;</hi> And for that onely reaſon (ſuch as it is) they can laviſh gold out of the bagge for the repayring its loſſes, and beautifying thereof: And being ſo repayred,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112349:14"/> they would undertake to defend and guard it all the dayes of their life.</p>
               <p>Why (wiſe men) would you doe ſo? If Silver and Gold be ſo plentifull with you, <hi>laviſh Gold out of the bagge, and weigh Silver in the ballance,</hi> and ſend it into Ireland. No, they will not heare of that, we knew that before; they that favour Croſſes, ſpeake, plead for, and love dead Images, hate the living; we know it by their practiſe; But yet I ſay, they have but this onely to ſay for the ſtanding of their Croſſe, <hi>It is an Ornament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What an Idoll? and yet an ornament; theſe words are as we uſe to ſay <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ye cannot make the words agree, an <hi>Idoll</hi> and an <hi>Abomination;</hi> there is an agreement: An Idoll! then downe with it even to the ground; that agrees well alſo, the ground, and an Idoll: Thence its originall, thither let it go. But they will not grant it to be an <hi>Idoll;</hi> an <hi>Image</hi> they will grant it to be, and no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>We ſay the <hi>Croſſe</hi> is an <hi>Idoll,</hi> therefore an abomination; they grant it to be an <hi>Image</hi> but no
<hi>Idoll;</hi> and allow <hi>ſervice</hi> to it, but no <hi>worſhip;</hi> that diſtinction is ridiculous.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BUt here they muſt yeeld more whether they will or no; it is the <hi>worke</hi> of mens hands wee ſay; ſo are your cloathes they ſay, and yet no <hi>Idoll.</hi> I cannot tell that, our cloathes may be
<hi>Idolls,</hi> and we little better, but I goe on; There is a <hi>bowing</hi> to it; therefore an <hi>Idoll</hi> ſay we: The <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> bow before it, not to it; he doth not terminate his <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> there, he is not ſuch a foole, but carryeth the <hi>worſhip</hi> through the <hi>Image</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> therefore no <hi>Idoll</hi> ſay they, an Image if wee will, and more they will not grant us; though we ſhould ſtrive tooth and nayle, hand and foot, yet we ſhall dragge them no further.</p>
               <p>Here would be a ſtrife about <hi>words</hi> and
<hi>Names;</hi> for two Names there are (we ſhall heare them anon) which yet ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie but one thing, differing no more then doe with us,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112349:15"/> our <hi>meate</hi> and <hi>food.</hi> According to the grave Counſell, I will <hi>leave it off before it be medled with</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 17.14.</note>, onely the Reader muſt know this; that our <hi>Men</hi> and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> goe along hand in hand thus farre; they doe allow of <hi>Images</hi> but no <hi>Idolls:</hi> and they know a way to give the <hi>Image</hi> its due, and God His, by a faire diſtinction, and keepe themſelves from Idolls well enough. There is they ſay <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> I know not how to Engliſh it to their minds, but I thinke it is this. There is <hi>Veneration</hi> and
<hi>Adoration,</hi> or if that like not, let it be <hi>worſhip</hi> and
<hi>ſervice.</hi> The firſt they give to God onely, the other to the Image (and yet no Idoll) <hi>They worſhip God and they ſerve Images:</hi> Here is a divided ſervice, like a ſhip cut in ſunder, neither Mine nor Thine, but the waters<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>lius N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rim ſi dividis nec tu nec ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitis. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crob. Sat.</hi> 2.
<hi>Cap.</hi> 6. 2 Kings 17.33. Verſ. 12. Verſ. 16. <hi>Jewel Ap. Art.</hi>
14.</note>: A mongrell Religion, like that we read of, <hi>they feared the Lord and ſerved Devills,</hi> for it was after the manner of the nations; next verſe you read, <hi>They feared not the Lord;</hi> no, He muſt have our
<hi>feare</hi> our <hi>worſhip</hi> and ſervice, and all; and the Image, as it is nothing, ſo muſt it have nothing at all. The forenamed Chapter will cleare it to us, that the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes acknowledge no ſuch diſtinction,
<hi>they ſerved Idolls and worſhipped the Hoſt of Heaven.</hi> But they, who would have further reſolution in ſo plaine a caſe, may reade our Churches <hi>Jewell</hi> (I could cite Greeke Authors here more then two or three) who brings the diſpute to this iſſue; there is no more diſtinction between <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Worſhip</hi> and
<hi>Service</hi> in the ſacred Scripture, then is betwixt <hi>operation</hi> and <hi>working.</hi> And ſo he tells us a ſhort but merry tale of the Phiſitians wife, and her opinion touching <hi>Pepper.</hi> The queſtion was amongſt the good wives, <hi>whether Pepper was hot or cold;</hi> both anſwered the <hi>Doctreſſe,</hi> It is hot in <hi>ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> but cold in <hi>working;</hi> there is the diſtinction, ſuttle enough for a woman, who findes it worke enough to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and guid one Tongue: the Mans diſtinction is no wiſer, who profeſſeth to underſtand three; for if I <hi>ſerve God</hi> aright, I <hi>worſhip</hi> Him aright; if a thing
<hi>operates</hi> well, it <hi>workes</hi> well, and if my <hi>meate</hi> be good my <hi>food</hi> is not bad: hee that underſtands neither
<hi>Greeke</hi> nor <hi>Latine</hi> underſtands theſe words, and no difference in them at all, we will then ſmile
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112349:15"/> at the diſtinction and let it goe, for wee muſt bee ſerious Though yet we will remember what Biſhop <hi>Jewell</hi> ſaid at this point alſo, <hi>What Religion is that, whoſe ſervice we cannot mention without ſuſpition of ſcoffing?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Cleare proofe made from the cleareſt light, and trueſt evidence, that Images are Idols.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOw we come cloſer to the buſineſſe, to prove that Croſſes, Crucifixes, Images, are Idolls. And to make this cleare we will:</p>
               <p>Firſt, Heare what the Papiſts ſay.</p>
               <p>Secondly, what our owne men muſt grant.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we will conſult with the Oracle, what the Word of God ſaith; I ſhall be ſhort in all this, for it were a ſhame to make it a long worke to prove a <hi>Croſſe</hi> an <hi>Idoll.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. What ſay the Papiſts? heare them if your eares can endure;
<note place="margin">a <hi>In Brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar infra heb. dom.</hi> 4.
<hi>quadra.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>All haile O Croſſe, our onely hope in this time of the paſſion, increaſe righteouſneſſe to the godly, and give pardon to guilty perſons.</hi> We have heard them with our eares, doe they not tingle? We will heare no more, for I doe aſſure the Reader, ſo many words as they have touching the Croſſe ſo many blaſphemies. I need not aske now, is the Croſſe an Idoll? The Papiſt will ſay, No, No? They bend before it, they pray unto it, then it is a God
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecce plumbatur, conſtruitur orig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tur, nec ad huc Deus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>. Ecce or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cratur, oratur, tunc poſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mo Deus eſt. Min. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l. infol. pag.</hi> 16.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 25.</note> whether the Papiſt will or no. But I have done with them, our eares are too chaſt to heare Blaſphemers: heare what our Men ſay, they are a little wiſer: and more ſober a little. What ſay they?</p>
               <p n="2">2. They ſay there is no Idolatry in the Croſſe, no Idoll ſervice given unto it, noue that they ſee. They ſee no ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding before it, nor praying unto it, ſo they ſay.</p>
               <p>We ſay, that ſurely they might ſee if they tooke time for obſervation, all that before mentioned, done before their Croſſe: others have ſeene it more then two or three times, I will name one in the Margent<note n="*" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Standiſh</hi> without Cripple gate.</note>, a man of good report.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112349:16"/> Certainly men and women both have beene obſerved to bow there, and to patter out we know not what, nor them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves neither.
<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the world lib. 1. Chap. 10 Sect.
7.</note> And the Divell heares them, that's certaine too: for there hee is crept into thoſe ſtockes and ſtones, and there hath nezled himſelf, as the learned Knight ſaith. Thoſe men might conſider, and they muſt grant unto us now, that that may be done before the Croſſe which they ſee not. And therefore I commaud from them now, what they cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny me, that is this,
<hi>That the Croſſe is ſubject to poſſibility of an Idolatrous uſe.</hi> This they muſt grant mee. For what though they would ſcorne to bend before a ſtocke? What though they ſee none that ſo doe? Yet it is
<hi>poſſible,</hi> that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe bow to it and pray before it too, I ſay there is a <hi>poſſibility,</hi> becauſe I will ſay no more but what they muſt yeeld me a <hi>poſſibility</hi> (though we know it is a
<hi>certainty,</hi> and hath beene ſo depoſed.) And now I command the reſt; Becauſe there is a <hi>poſſibilitie,</hi> that thereby many may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and thruſt away from the ſervice and pure worſhip of God; what followes then? Therefore it is nought and muſt be throwne downe. Then take away the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> both, for <hi>Papiſts Idolize</hi> the one and Drunkards the other. True, but here is a wide difference; Bread is of Gods inſtitution, ſo is not the
<hi>Croſſe,</hi> therefore downe with it, thine eye ſhall not pitty it, neither ſhalt thou ſpare, (no, though it be thy Brother, Sonne, daughter, wife, if theſe or any of theſe would thruſt thee from thy God) but downe with it even to the ground; becauſe there is a <hi>poſſibility,</hi> it may thruſt thee away from the Lord thy God.</p>
               <p>We muſt avoyd all <hi>poſſibility</hi> of Idolatry, all things that may lead that way; and walke on ſtreight, turning to nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, in a right path, the way of the upright, for that is ſafe. There is a worſhip of God (a worſhip in ſpirit and in truth) which is not ſubject to a poſſibility of being Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous: For there is no poſſibility of darkeneſſe in Light, no poſſibility of evill in goodneſſe. A wiſe man takes a ſafe path.</p>
               <p>So we have heard what our men ſay and what they muſt grant,
<hi>A poſſibilitie of Idolatry in the Croſſe.</hi> And then what
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112349:16"/> is drawne and commanded from them by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, <hi>The Croſſe muſt downe even to the ground.</hi> It muſt not be ſpared nor pittied, that hand which holds it up is as he who builds the walls; which God hath curſt. Now wee enquire of the ſacred Scripture, that will put the matter out of queſtion, not that there is a poſſibility of Idolatry in <hi>Croſſe-ſervice,</hi> but that it is the greateſt Idolatry that ever was in the world.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What ſaith the word, wee are charged to heare that; thus we reade
<note place="margin">Eſay
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.28.</note>
                  <hi>their Land alſo is full of Idolls, they worſhip the workes of their owne hands, that which their owne ſingers have made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi>
                  </note>How proves he that?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>They <hi>bowed</hi> before it, they <hi>humbled</hi> themſelves unto it: ſo we read in the next Verſe, and a fearefull judgement fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>therefore forgive them not.</hi> Why? They <hi>bowed,</hi> they <hi>humbled</hi> themſelves before Wood and Stone: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obj.</hi>
                  </note>The adverſary replyes, that in that Scripture there is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Idolls</hi> not of
<hi>Images;</hi> of bowing before Idolls, (bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before an Image makes it an Idoll, but let it goe, and let them goe on) we ſpeake for Images, and the fellow brings us a Scripture againſt Idolls, which we condemne as well as he, ſo they ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>Now I muſt turne them to another ſacred Scripture, what finde we there? That which ſhould make us tremble for there we finde the <hi>Lord provoked to anger,</hi> and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Lord is like the roaring of a Lyon, which makes the Beaſt of the Forreſt to tremble. But what provokes the Lord. Idolls I warrant you: Yes, they ever were, are, and will be a great provocation, <hi>a ſmoake in His noſe, and a fire that burneth all the day.</hi> But yet this word is not mentioned there, but ſuch things as yee ſee in Cheapſide, or ſome of the Chappells, <hi>Graven Images,</hi> ſo we reade,
<note place="margin">Jer. 8.19.</note>
                  <hi>They provoked Me with graven Images, and with ſtrange vanities.</hi> And how then? how doth it appeare that God was provoked with that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple becauſe of their Images? By the heat of His diſpleaſure, it abideth upon them, it ſcorcheth them at this day, as the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112349:17"/> Midſommer Sunne doth the earth at mid day. Indeed it is as cleare as the Sunſhine, when neither miſt nor cloud ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, overſhadowing the ſame: But I keepe to the Text; though they thought themſelves in a ſecure eſtate, <hi>Is not the Lord in Zyon?</hi> though they looked good would come to them from this place, and from that by meanes here or there, yet no good came, none at all, Their Images,
<hi>ſtrange vanities</hi> ſtopt the paſſage. We looked ſay they to that hill, and that mountaine, to this time, and to that, now helpe would be; but our eye failed with expectation, no helpe came, <hi>The harveſt is paſt, the Summer is ended, and we are not ſaved:</hi> Let us ponder, and well weigh the words; I goe on to a third Scripture, where they muſt well conſider. how an Idoll is deſcribed, <hi>A thing wrought according to a mans owne underſtanding;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſea 13.2.</note> that is an Idoll: When a man in the worſhip of God, will frame ſomething ſuteable to his owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reaſon, then he makes Idolls. If we would worſhip God purely, (elſe not at all) then we muſt mingle nothing of our owne, nothing of our owne wiſedome, underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, reaſon: if we doe, wee marre all. Wee muſt be ſuch fooles, as to yeeld our eare wholly up to heare what God ſaith, and follow cloſe what hee commands touching His Worſhip. It followes, <hi>All of it the worke of the Craftsman.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chryſ. in <hi>Eſay</hi> 2. Qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam eſſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Yes, he makes
<hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> this goddeſſe and the other, he doth the deed; I know this is
<hi>blaſphemy,</hi> but I muſt ſay as he doth, with one piece of the blocke he hath heated his ſhins; with another piece of the blocke he roſteth his meat; and of the remainder he makes a god, for he reſolves to bow before it. No man is ſuch a foole, as to bow before a lumpe of gold, or a wooden ſtocke, for then as he goes through Cheapſide or through a Forreſt, he muſt bow at every ſtep. But the Craftsman comes, that daring fellow, the god-maker, hee poliſheth it <hi>according to his underſtanding,</hi> then it is a god; and then it followes, <hi>they kiſſe the Calves.</hi> I doe not thinke ſo, no more then the Papiſts doe kiſſe their <hi>Idolls.</hi> They bowed and did ſome reverence before it, ſo they <hi>kiſſed</hi> them: Now we have the deſcription of an
<hi>Idoll,</hi> and it ſufficeth. Yes, it ſufficeth to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112349:17"/> perſwade men that have reaſon and faith too; but not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, being barely read and no more, to perſwade with
<hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable</hi> and <hi>wicked men,</hi> and to <hi>deliver</hi> us from them; therefore let us conclude with the prayer in that place,
<q rend="inline">
                     <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.1,2.</note>"that the word of the Lord may have free courſe &amp; be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified:</q> That is the ready way to be delivered from unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and wicked men; from the miſchiefe of Idolls and Idoll makers, <hi>David</hi> could not tell which of the twaine was the verieſt ſtocke. But let us well conſider the judgement that followeth. They made <hi>Idolls according to their owne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding;</hi> They <hi>kiſſed the Calves,</hi> what if they did?
<hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſhall be as the morning cloud, as the early Dew, as the Chaffe driven with a whirlewind, and as the ſmoake out of the Chimney.</hi> Marke it good Reader, as a <hi>morning cloud;</hi> how quickly diſpelled? As an <hi>early dew,</hi> how ſoone dryed up?<note place="margin">Hoſea
13.3.</note> as <hi>the chaffe,</hi> a little wind drives it, a greater whirles it we know not whether; as the <hi>Smoak,</hi> how preſently it vaniſheth? See the condition of <hi>Idolls</hi> and <hi>Idoll</hi> men, and their burden from the Lord!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Though the proofes cleare the Croſſe to be an Idoll, yet it muſt not downe they ſay, becauſe it is an ornament. Their ſaying is weighed at the Sanctuary and found to be as light as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, The greateſt Prophets, and the beſt Kings defiled their Image and their Ornament both.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BUt now if they ſhould grant us, that the <hi>Croſſe</hi> is an <hi>Idoll,</hi> which they muſt doe, if they grant a
<hi>poſſibility</hi> that any knee ever hath in former time, or ever may in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time bend before it: Why yet they vvill never grant but that it may be an <hi>ornament</hi> for all that, and therefore may ſtand to beautifie the place as it hath done: There lyeth the pith of their reaſon, <hi>It is an ornament,</hi> therefore let it ſtand, and let it be maintayned in a
<hi>poſture of defence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be it ſo, but they ſhall never thrive with that Argument, as much might have beene ſaid for the Image in the 3. of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell:</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:112349:18"/> without controverſie a goodly Image, and beautifying the place very much to the outward eye: And as much for the Queene Mothers Idoll, which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her ſonne cut downe and <hi>ſtamped it,</hi> vvhether under his feet or to powder, I cannot tell: but, in an holy indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he ſtamped it and burnt <hi>it at the brooke Kidron.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 15.16.</note> And more might be ſaid why the Brazen-Serpent might be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which yet we read was brake to peeces, and muſt bee called by its Name, plaine Braſſe now, and of no more uſe. Much alſo might be ſaid why the <hi>Chariots</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> might be ſpared; for they were goodly Chariots, and for beauty and outward excellency, farre exceeding the Croſſe, or any one Croſſe in the world; and yet the good King <hi>burnt them with fire.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King.
23.11.</note> Nay I doe verily beleeve, the Calfe was a goodly peece of workmanſhip, great coſt beſtowed upon it; and doubtleſſe, though but a <hi>Calfe,</hi> yet the moſt ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Calfe that ever was ſeene in the world, for they turned <hi>their glory into it:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal.
106.20.</note> And why might not that bee ſuffered to ſtand for an ornament? <hi>Moſes</hi> will reſolve that, not by his word, but by his hand: Surely he ſaw reaſon good enough, elſe he had not beene carried with ſuch indignation againſt it, as we read <hi>He burnt it in the fire.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 32.20.</note> There was an end of a Molten-Calfe. Nay not yet; <hi>he ground it to powder.</hi> Then it was ſmall enough, it could never be put together againe; no, but the people might have
<hi>pittied the Duſt thereof, therefore he ſtrewed it upon the water,</hi> they ſhould never ſee it again. Yes, but they might, the water might caſt it forth, and leave ſome Aſhes upon the ſand. Therefore he <hi>made the Children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael drinke of it;</hi> now the nature of it was changed quite. When Idolls are dealt withall, then behold not a cutting downe onely, but a ſtamping, a burning, an utter aboliſhing: becauſe the heart is ſo prone to <hi>Idolatrous worſhip.</hi> Truely me thinkes if theſe men will ſlightly paſſe over what theſe good Kings did, <hi>Aſa</hi> and
<hi>Hezekiah,</hi> when they were dealing with Idols how they brake them to peeces and ſtamped them to powder: yet they ſhould regard what
<hi>Moſes</hi> did in ſuch a caſe; for that is moſt notable, and he the greateſt Prophet that ever was, and faithfull in all the houſe, his example
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112349:18"/> ſhould be obſerved and followed. But notwithſtanding theſe Men well never have done Reaſoning and queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. I will take leave to put one queſtion, there is but one Anſwer to make to it, therefore we cannot miſſe of it: And the Anſwer will be to the ſhame of their owne faces and confuſion of <hi>Idolls</hi> for ever. The Queſtion is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why might no man know where Moſes Sepulcher was?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 34.8.</note> The Anſwer muſt be; <hi>for fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of an Idolatrous worſhip:</hi> had the people knowne the place, they would have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the mould there, and kiſſed his bones. Hee was the greateſt Prophet in the world, and had the moſt honorable buriall that ever any man before or ſince that time; for
<hi>the Lord buried him.</hi> The people who ſaid to a <hi>molten Calfe</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Exod. 32.4,5.</note>, <hi>They be thy gods,</hi> and dedicated a <hi>feaſt</hi> to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the Calfe I meane: doubtleſſe they would have done as much to <hi>Moſes</hi> body; therefore there was ſuch a <hi>contention about it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>i</hi> Jude. 9.</note> Did the Devill ſtrive about a dead mans body for any love or delight in the ſame? No, the Devills ayme was to gaine the hearts of the people, to ſet up an Idoll for himſelfe there, that was his ayme, therefore he contended; and he gaines much upon us this way, by preſentations to the eye. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath he many
<hi>reliques,</hi> I know not what, nor of whom, but <hi>pretious</hi> things they ſay, and with thoſe (toyes and knackes) he takes the ſimple ones every day; he hath alſo gloriouſneſſe of Altars, infinite number of Images, prieſtly ornaments very coſtly; and divers fopperies about his ſervice, all to catch the affections of thoſe, who not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the truth in love, are given up to beleeve lies.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi>
                  </note>Now I can anſwer their queſtion too, why may not the Croſſe, be it an Image or (as the Roundheads ſay) an <hi>Idoll,</hi> yet why may it not ſtand? it hath ſtood there time out of minde, why may it not ſtand till the worlds end?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>I might anſwer, it may not; becauſe it is an offence and griefe of heart to the ſtrong Chriſtian; a ſtumbling blocke to the weake; a very downefall to the ſtubborne and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. But this one anſwer ſhall ſerve, though they ſhould aske till to morrow morning; <hi>For feare of an Idolatrous worſhip;</hi> therefore the Croſſe muſt not ſtand. <hi>There is poſſibilitie of</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:112349:19"/> 
                  <hi>it, at the leaſt it may draw us from God,</hi> therefore the Croſſe muſt downe.</p>
               <p>I know their mindes; they are not ſatisfied herewith. They will keepe up the Croſſe notwithſtanding all that I have ſayd, or any man elſe can ſay. Very good reaſon they ſhould doe as they ſay, maintaine the ſtanding of the Croſſe notwithſtanding what I have ſayd, or any man elſe: for what are mans words, mine or anothers? But if I have ſpoken out of the Word of God, and by authoritie thereof: They might have ſo much manners (being reaſonable and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous men, not halfe ſo obſtinate as are downe-right Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, whoſe will is their reaſon) to regard what the Lord ſaith. What though no argument which I have given, is ſufficient why it ſhould downe (and inſufficient be it, if it be not the cleare Word of God) is not Gods Word e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough? His charge ſufficient? <hi>Yee ſhall, &amp;c. Deut.</hi> 12.2. Is not His prohibition ſtrong enough?
<hi>Thou ſhalt make no graven Image, &amp;c.</hi> And in the laſt place is it not enough? That in this caſe, and to teach us what to doe, we have the example of the beſt Kings and the wiſeſt Prophets? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this isenough, if we have not to do with wicked and unreaſonable men. I will then be pretty confident, having brought no word againſt this Image but what hath cleare ground in the Word of God;</p>
               <p>That the Image is an Idoll; Why? what more Why's yet? It was anſwered before, becauſe there is as much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>kiſſing</hi> an Image now, as there was once of <hi>kiſſing</hi> a dead mans bones, or the mould there; therefore an Idoll, and then an abomination, and muſt downe; nay it muſt be defiled and its <hi>ornament</hi> alſo, and the
<hi>heart</hi> muſt doe it; and that will fret us to the heart, and make tumults and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtions in the world now, and more anon: It followes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:112349:19"/>
               <head>SECT. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ornament of Images muſt be defiled with the hand and heart both; the moſt High God will have it ſo; and the ſtouteſt heart in the world muſt bend here or breake. But before this be done, looke to heare of warres and rumors of warres.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SUppoſe now theſe men ſhould grant us this (and it were a large grant) that the Croſſe is an Idoll, and muſt bee caſt downe; though they are ſo pittifull, they have not the heart to doe it themſelves, yet they will ſuffer it to be done, ſuppoſe I ſay, they will yeeld ſo farre; why yet they will checke at two things; firſt, <hi>they would not have their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament defiled,</hi> and about this though wee could contend mightily, with our tongues, and hands, and hearts, and all, yet we muſt yeeld, for God will overcome at the laſt: The ſecond ſhall be granted them, <hi>they ſhall have an ornament;</hi> but of that in due place.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as <hi>Amaziah</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">2 Chro.
25.9.</note> but what ſhall wee doe for the three hundred Talents? ſo alſo; They have laviſhed gold out of the bagge, and weighed ſilver in the ballance, and hired a cunning workeman, who hath made a god of it, muſt they now looſe all their coſt? now that the leg, and thigh, and noſe are ſtript off, may they not make uſe of the deckings and adornings which are upon the remayning parts? The meaning is for we will come to a low rate, may they not reſerve the <hi>ſcrapings</hi> of their Images? the old ends of gold and ſilver there? Truely no; for, ſuppoſe they ſhould reſerve what is pleaſing in their eyes, and to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; yet what could they doe with it? That is eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, you will ſay;
<note place="margin">Pro. 17.3.</note>
                  <hi>The fining pot is for ſilver, and the furnace for golda</hi>. True, but all the fining pots in the world and a furnace ſeaven times heated cannot purifie and refine that ſilver and gold; for now it is put upon an Idoll, it is an accurſed thing.</p>
               <p>Theſe men will not beleeve me now, and no matter; I am very well contented ſtill that my words be ſlighted. But
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112349:20"/> I pray you &amp; them, let us heare what the
<hi>Lord</hi> ſaith, as we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire &amp; expect that He ſhould heare us in the day of our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when we ſhall call to Him, <hi>make haſte Lord to our helpe, make no tarrying.</hi> Such a time will be, let us heare Him now (that is the ready way to be heard then) and chew upon His words now one after another; and as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>eate them.</hi> What ſaith the Lord?
<hi>yee ſhall defile.</hi> What is that? Why, you ſuppoſe ſome ſanctitie &amp; holineſſe in an image; ſee now, you muſt
<hi>defile</hi> it; that is, you muſt deale with it, as with the vileſt, filthieſt, moſt contemptible thing that your eye can looke upon; as
<hi>Moſes</hi> dealt with the Calfe; King <hi>Aſa</hi> with the Queene Mothers Image; King <hi>Ezekiah</hi> with the Brazen Serpent, and Chariots of the Sunne; ſo muſt you <hi>defile</hi> the Images. We remember very well what <hi>overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, breaking, hewing downe, deſtroying, ſtamping, burning, drowning, eating,</hi> there was when they ſet upon this worke of defiling; ſo we muſt defile Images.</p>
               <p>Pretty flexible they are; ſo they will defile the
<hi>ſtone,</hi> and the <hi>wood,</hi> and the <hi>lead,</hi> ſuch poore ſtuffe; and ſo I have drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them on a little further: but for the ſilver and gold, the rich &amp; pretious things, the Lord muſt pardon them for that, they have not the heart to defile ſuch good things. No; they will heare, I hope what the Lord ſaith, and heare Him out; then they muſt
<hi>defile</hi> the ſilver and the gold, for the Lord will have it ſo;
<note place="margin">Eſa 30.22.</note> yee ſhall defile the
<hi>covering</hi> of the graven Images of ſilver, and <hi>ornament</hi> of gold. Obſerve we well, the <hi>covering</hi> of ſilver, the
<hi>ornament</hi> of gold, pretious ſtuffe I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you; yet it muſt be defiled. Truely I am perſwaded ſo well of the civility of thoſe men, that
<hi>ne <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> quidem,</hi> they will not ſo much as mutter (pine perhaps) at all this, for theſe are the words and charge of the Lord.</p>
               <p>But now they thinke verily, they have done the deed, the Image is defiled according to the Word of the Lord. No not yet; the maine and chiefe worke is yet behind; a work that will plunge the ſtouteſt Papiſt in the world, and bring him to his knees, before he doth it. Alas, the hardeſt part of the worke is yet behind. All the defiling hitherto is done by the hand; now the <hi>heart</hi> muſt bee imployed too, and then the worke will be done indeed. We commonly ſay
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112349:20"/> and we ſay very well, <hi>What the heart doth not doe, is not done.</hi> Many motives and by-ends may carry the hand to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing theſe Images, their coverings, and ornaments too. The Ruler may command me <hi>(in the Lord)</hi> then I muſt <hi>obey:</hi> vaine glory, a zeale for our owne houſe, to get my ſelfe a Name, ſo <hi>Jehu</hi> was moved. But it is a cleane and pure zeale, which mooves the heart with an indignation againſt them, and ſets that a worke to defile the ſame: Marke wee now; Images are moſt filthy things, and thy heart muſt riſe againſt them with a loathing of them, and ſo to defile them, as ſuch things thou canſt not looke upon and wilt not name, they are ſo filthy. So we reade on,
<hi>Thou ſhalt caſt them away as a menſtruous cloth:</hi> thou ſhalt ſay unto them, as to that thy ſoule abhorres, and is an offence of heart unto thee, <hi>get thee hence.</hi> Certainly the Lord God, even the Lord God,
<hi>Who is the bleſſed and onely potentate, the King of Kings and Lord of Lords</hi> hath fully anſwered them at this point.<note place="margin">1 Tim.
6.15.</note> Doubtleſſe the proudeſt man upon earth dares not anſwer againe, nay, hee dares not whiſper. Thus Idols muſt be defiled; It is a worke which commands the heart, and there are great thoughts of heart about it. I proceed on to make ſome diſcovery of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How vaine and brutiſh mans thoughts have been and are touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Images, and the defiling of them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Cannot paſſe this point, for it is a diſcovering point: what my thoughts were about it, I ſhall ſpeake out to my ſhame; I care not ſo God may be glorified in mee, or by me. Truely, I ſhall tell a faire tale of my ſelfe now, <hi>how bruiiſh I was and ignorant, even as beaſt before Thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">† 1. Time was when I thought <hi>Croſſes</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> were prettie gaudy things; made onely for children to gaze up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Croſſe in the horne-booke, pictures and babies, and the like. It was a childiſh thought, and may paſſe well
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112349:21"/> enough: when I was a childe, I thought as a child, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as a child, and did as a child, I delighted in poppets, I played with pictures, and rid a gallop upon a long Reed: but when I became a man, I put away thoſe childiſh things, and yet my thoughts touching Images were not ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a man of underſtanding, for thus I thought,
<hi>What hurt is in a Crucifix?</hi> It will ſerve the Lay-man (I know not who that is, but that is the word in uſe) in ſtead of a booke; and is able to worke much upon his Imagination, and to affect his heart by his eye.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui crea vit me de dit mihi poteſtatem creandiſe Apol. Page</hi> 260.</note> Theſe were wiſe thoughts. By the good hand of God upon me, I rectified them thus;
<q rend="inline">"That nothing was ſet downe by the Evangeliſts touching the <hi>complexion, ſtature, feature</hi> of
<hi>Chriſt:</hi> why? That no man might preſume to ſet his hand to the framing of that aſtoniſhing worke, wrought once for all, by the Holy Ghoſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Much ſhould be ſaid here: I intend a very little: I weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the words which I finde cited by our <hi>Jewell,</hi> touching the bold blaſphemy of this god-maker; <hi>He that made mee, hath given me power to make him:</hi> that is good divinitie thought I, but the good Biſhop anſwers him very well;
<q rend="inline">"<hi>God hath made hell fire to the deſtruction of all them, that yeeld their mouth to ſuch blaſphemy:</hi>
                  </q> I inſtance here in the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> becauſe that is the Image moſt in uſe, and moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly framed. I goe on to tell how I came to bee reſolved and ſetled in my judgement, that there ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Images at all, I meane ſuch as were lately defiled.
<hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> hath much againſt them; <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith more to our purpoſe, we will heare him.<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſiote me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mores, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecti filii, ne in eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam, &amp;c. Sed perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rte Deum in cordibus veſtris &amp;c, Non enim fas eſt Chriſtianos per oculos ſuſpenſum teneri ſed p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>: Jewell Apol. page</hi> 553. <hi>Non
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> eſt quin religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ulla ſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>bicun qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacrum eſt. l.</hi> 2.
<hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note>
                  <q rend="inline">"My deare children be yee mindfull that we bring no Images into the Church: But evermore carry God in your hearts thither, and forth againe. Nay ſuffer not Images to be in your private hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they will undoe you, for it is not lawfull to lead a Chriſtian man by his eyes, but rather by the ſtudy and exerciſe of his minde.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeakes home and convinced me clearly; theſe are his words, <hi>Determinately and out of all douht, there is no religion where there is an Image;</hi> that is, <hi>no Religion</hi> which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112349:21"/> God accounts of; it is a <hi>Religion,</hi> but ſuch as his ſoule hates. There are no people under heaven ſo rude, brutiſh, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, but have ſome Religion amongſt them: The
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> veru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. de
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ello ſacro p.</hi> 339.</note>
                  <hi>Turks</hi> have a Religion, and others as bruitiſh as they, whom
<hi>David</hi> calls
<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.30.</note>
                  <hi>the multitude of the Bulls, with the Calves of the people;</hi>
                  <q rend="inline">"<hi>That is no Religion in Gods account, which is not comely for a Chriſtian.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt note in the laſt place (for I doe but point at things) that this conſideration wrought with me moſt of all how the anger of the Lord hath ſmoaked againſt His owne people becauſe of their Images and Idoll ſervices; <hi>They tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the glory of God into a lie;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore the Lord turned them out of the good land, out of the place of their habitation; He <hi>ſwept</hi> them away, and <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped</hi> them as one wipeth a diſh, turning it upſide downe;<note place="margin">2 King. 17 2 King. 21 13.</note> ſee! theſe Images, and that Idoll ſervice can ſtocke up a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by the root. Certainly thought I, theſe things, that provoke the Lord to anger, that makes His wrath burne to the neathermoſt hell, are pernicious things, and to be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as we heard. And God be thanked, Who hath ſo taught me and inſtructed to diſcretion; that I may be warned and learne to abominate Images as the Jewes doe, for ſo it is clearely intimated, <hi>I will recompence thy way upon thine head, and thou ſhalt not commit this lewdneſſe above all thine abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.43.</note> But I muſt goe on to tell how bruitiſh my thoughts were; I have not told the halfe yet.</p>
               <p n="2">† 2. Time was when I thought, that to defile an Image had beene an eaſie worke; caſt a little durt in its face, then it is defiled; and if you wrench from it his <hi>leg</hi> and his <hi>noſe</hi> then you have defiled him utterly: Such were my bruitiſh conceits. Verily thought I the command is very eaſie to fleſh and blood, <hi>Turne your ſelves from your Idols, and your faces from all your abominations:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 14.6.</note> the eaſieſt matter in the world: if I
<hi>turne</hi> my backe upon them, I am <hi>turned;</hi> and if you
<hi>turne</hi> a man into the Church; perſwade with him to heare Gods Word conſtantly there, then you have <hi>turned</hi> the man, and he is turned from his Idols. A bruitiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; it was mine. I thanke the Lord and his good Word
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112349:22"/> I am better inſtructed now; that a man muſt <hi>turne</hi> from his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>loathſome</hi> things, and his <hi>face</hi> from them, as
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth abhorre and abominate; then his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and then it is done: Now the man is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> goes to the very heart, and of that anon; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> adde here; that to turne from an Idoll is to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>geſt motion in the world; and to caſt it out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is to caſt out ones <hi>ſelfe,</hi> which will never be done till God, who turned
<hi>Jurdan</hi> backe, gives in His <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and then it will be done. I goe on to make my bruitiſh thoughts more legible yet, that they who obſerve them may be made wiſer thereby.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:idagger"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>inverted †</ex>
                  </expan> 3. I verily thought, that every Idoll had a face like a man, and a <hi>Noſe</hi> there, which might be defiled before he was aware; and ſtollen away while he was aſleepe; It muſt needs drop from out of the hands and fingers ends of ſome cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning workeman; hee onely makes Idols thought I: And they are no where to be found but in the Popes Chappells, or in other out-places by the appointment of his holineſſe, and of his Deputie-Lievtenants upon earth. Were not theſe wiſe thoughts, thinke you? And no wiſer could my conceit be touching <hi>Idolaters,</hi> ſuch onely, thought I, as doe bow before ſtockes and ſtones, and humble themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Table.</hi> They indeed are groſſe <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and no other in the world. I thanke the Lord who hath better inſtructed me: I know now by ſad experience, that I have one within me, the moſt cunning Idoll framer in the world. I Muſt ſpeak the truth, God is at my right hand; whatſoever was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant &amp; deſirable in my eyes or to my underſtanding (being but a creature) he I am ſpeaking of, can make an Idoll of it; &amp; ſo it hath done, and made me ſmart ſoundly according to the threat; <hi>Their ſorrowes ſhall be multiplyed that haſten after another God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.4.</note> What hee made my Idoll, God made my Croſſe: bleſſed be His Name. I could not paſſe this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obſervation, what a cunning Deceiver and Idoll-maker every man (for I thinke heart anſwers heart, as face anſwers face in water) hath within his owne breaſt: And let the Child in underſtanding obſerve it; That if the <hi>heart</hi> had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112349:22"/> not made and ſet up that abomination in that <hi>Holy</hi> of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> (ſo it ſhould be kept) there had never beene an <hi>Idoll</hi> made of Wood and Stone in the world, nor ſet up before their eyes there. This might have bin reſelved for the
<hi>Cloſet;</hi> But I muſt goe on to tell, that in my Cloſet and Temple worke, I have beene an <hi>Abominable Idolater:</hi> This <hi>Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> hath beguiled me even in matters concerning the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice of my God. I regarded onely the outſide of the ſervice, and if it was performed, if I had ſaid my prayers I had done my dutie and it was enough; for the manner how (which is all in Gods ſervice) it was no matter. But that very conceit made it an <hi>Idol ſervice,</hi> which I conſidered not: ſo alſo the courſe of the world, the rudiments there; all theſe were Idols unto me: Then could I ſet up my <hi>Thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold</hi> by the <hi>Lords Threſhold,</hi> and my <hi>Poſt</hi> by His <hi>Poſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 43.8. <hi>Adhibendo traditiones ſuas ad prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta ſua Junius.</hi> Joh. 4.23. Jer. 1.31. <hi>In cult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> dei ceſſare debent quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid eſt prud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntiae quicquid rattonis in hominibus quicquid conſilii &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nique omnes eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ſus nam ſi hic tantilinm ſibi permi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unt, nihil a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iud q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am Dei cultum vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>era idola colunt.</hi>
                  </note> that is, I could mate the wiſedome of God in His ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, inſtitutions and commands with my follies, the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my owne inventions: I could frame ſomething even in the worſhip of God ſutable to my owne judgement and reaſon; and I could thinke it as good every whit as that, which God appointed, not conſidering what manner of ſervice God commands, nor what <hi>worſhippers Hee ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi> It is not utterable how bold and daring the heart will be, to intrude upon the ordinances of God, mingling ſuch things therewith, which
<q rend="inline">"He never commanded nor ever came <hi>into His heart.</hi>
                  </q>We goe a whoring after our owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions. The heart told me, that the Croſſe in Baptiſme was as innocent a ceremony as the Popes Name.
<hi>What great matter to make a Croſſe upon the forhead with your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</hi> Yes, it is a great matter, and a very <hi>Idoll</hi> ſaith judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in</hi> upon
<hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.2. for it is an <hi>addition</hi> of man
<q rend="inline">"according to his owne underſtanding,</q> others can ſtand it out perhaps ſtoutly enough: my underſtanding muſt bee carryed captive by the Word of God, not regarding what others ſay who ſpeake their owne words. Let me fall flat under the power and authoritie of that ſacred Scripture, which tells me, I muſt not ſerve God after my owne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner according to my <hi>owne underſtanding</hi> (for then <hi>I</hi> make it an <hi>Idoll</hi> ſervice) but as God hath commanded thereafter <hi>I</hi> muſt doe.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112349:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:112349:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:112349:24"/> 
                  <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſay leaſt of that, whereof <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſay moſt; how <hi>I</hi> made an <hi>Idoll</hi> of both Sacraments, <hi>I</hi> thought of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> as the Jewes of their <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> that there was no other but what was made
<hi>with hands: I</hi> dreamed not of a <hi>Baptiſme</hi> made without hands, with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt and with fire.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 3.11.</note> And ſo this followed, a groſſe and an idolatrous conceit; <hi>I</hi> thought it enough, that <hi>I</hi> had a ſprinkling of water upon my face, or was <hi>dipped</hi> there, and ſo was made a Chriſtian out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in name and in a bare profeſſion onely. But when <hi>I</hi> conſidered two Scriptures,<note place="margin">Jer. 9.25 26. Rom. 2.28</note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> ſaw it as cleare as the Sunne, that the Baptiſme of fire and of the Holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſt; ſome <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worke</hi> was to be looked after; for the <hi>outward,</hi> if no more, did but intitle me to a bare name onely, gave me no preheminence at all above the heathen; rather thruſt mee downe below them, and aggravated my guilt<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> de g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r. l.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>pag.</hi> 145. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eg: pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> muſt acknowledge in the next place, how <hi>I</hi> made an <hi>Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> of the other
<hi>Sacrament;</hi> not but that <hi>I</hi> did <hi>ſee</hi> and
<hi>feele</hi> and <hi>taſt</hi> the bread and wine there. My
<hi>Idolatry</hi> was of a ſiner thread, yet very groſſe and palpable, ſuch as I can feele now: for I looked not to the <hi>heart</hi> and
<hi>ſoule</hi> of the Sacrament; neither how I came addreſſed thereto, what bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe of heart I brought thither; what life of affection, what ſtrength of faith: Thither I came according to cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and after the courſe of the world, dragging my heart thither, and not my heart me; and there I ſate accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to forme, and went away after the manner: Let it be conſidered whether this be not to make an <hi>Idoll</hi> of a moſt ſacred and miſterious ordinance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> ſhould paſſe on to that monſtrous <hi>Idoll Selfe Righteonſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> which takes up ſo much roome in the heart, that there is no place for the righteouſneſſe of another; hath blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted much Paper, and ſtained, yea ſpoyled all our good workes. <hi>I</hi> ſhould alſo ſpeak ſomething touching the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of defiling that monſter (ſo <hi>Luther</hi> calls it) and theſe gods before pointed at; for if that be not done nothing is done, and if that be done, all is done; if the <hi>Idols</hi> in the heart are caſt out thence and defiled, ſtocks and ſtones cannot ſtand before the eye, they ſhall be defiled too: but as the ſaying is, this is all the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112349:24"/> 
                  <hi>labour,</hi> this the <hi>worke</hi> indeed: I can ſay but this to it in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Pauls</hi> words and
<hi>Luthers</hi> after him:<note place="margin">Gal. 1.15. See <hi>Luther</hi> his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition thereon.</note> When God is <hi>pleaſed</hi> (what? for my phariſaicall Religion, or my blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe life in my conceit? for my prayers, faſtings, and good workes? No, much leſſe then for my abominations, my doting upon my <hi>Idols,</hi> every thing my heart could delight in: <hi>Is</hi> He pleaſed with this? No, how then? <hi>For His meere grace alone</hi>) <hi>to reveale His Sonne unto me:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I ſhall turne indeed and indeed from <hi>Idols,</hi> and my face from all my abominations, then <hi>I</hi> am ſure (for ſo it hath beene, and ſo it is with all the faithfull and true Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents, ſo they and ſo <hi>I</hi>)
<note place="margin">Ezek. 6.9. 20.43.</note> ſhall
<hi>loath</hi> my Gods, and my ſelfe becauſe <hi>I</hi> made them ſo. Then my heart muſt defile his <hi>Idols,</hi> and when the heart doth it, then it is done. But here the heart will ſtand out, maintayning his ſtrong holds while it hath a being (in its ſelfe and upon his owne bottome:) he will maintaine his <hi>Idol</hi> as long as he can, and maintaine war againſt him, that would deſtroy it and take it away. <hi>I</hi> goe on to make yet more manifeſt thoſe thoughts of heart about this defiling worke, which may yeeld us a good underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of our Selves, and of the Times, and then <hi>I</hi> am at my <hi>Marke,</hi> the <hi>White I</hi> aime at, and would carry all unto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The heart, to maintaine its Idoll, maintaines warre againſt him, that would ſmite at it, and defile the ſame. He will not yeeld up his ſtrong hold while he hath a being in himſelfe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TIme was when I thought I could reade another mans heart better then mine owne; and others to be mad and my ſelfe a ſober man. <hi>I</hi> looked into the ſecond Chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and found an
<hi>Iraelite</hi> there, <hi>I</hi> thought, if there were a man in the world at that time mad and beſide himſelfe, that was he. <hi>Moſes</hi> would have given him good counſell, and have reformed him, how doth he accept of ſuch a kindneſſe? (for truly he that ſeekes to reforme me, does me the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112349:25"/> kindneſſe that can be imagined; for he that would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy my <hi>Idol</hi> would ſave my ſoule) How doth that
<hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite</hi> accept the kindneſſe of his friend? As we read,
<hi>Intendeſt thou to kill me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 2.14.</note> There we may obſerve how hee requited the loving kindneſſe of a friend, he counted <hi>reforming</hi> a <hi>killing;</hi> it was a death to him to bee counſelled and reformed: he was not himſelfe ſure when he ſpake ſo, and ſo <hi>I</hi> thought. See now how <hi>I</hi> could judge another man to be mad, who ſtands or falls to his owne Maſter: there is no man if the Lords hand hath not beene upon his heart to tame it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, and bring it into order, but is as ſtout and mad as was he; nay, more beſides himſelfe, then was that <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he may have a greater light to walke by than had that <hi>Iſraelite;</hi> for he lived in
<hi>Egypt,</hi> we live in the <hi>Goſhen</hi> of the world. This then is the concluſion;
<q rend="inline">"That the heart ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in its old poſture, and frame, ſetled upon its owne bottome and principles, ſtands as oppoſite to reformation or ſound counſell (<hi>I</hi> will take the former word all along) as the two poles, which the Aſtronomers call in Engliſh <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> or as are <hi>life</hi> and
<hi>death:</hi> And the demands of the one from the other are as contrary too, and muſt be ſo. And it is as impoſſible for man, nay for all the men on the earth, to make a good underſtanding betwixt theſe two,
<hi>Reformation</hi> and the <hi>Heart</hi> as to bring the <hi>North</hi> and the <hi>South</hi> together, thoſe two poles which ſtand at an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall oppoſition, or to make an agreement betwixt the Temple of God, and
<hi>Idolls,</hi> ſire and water, life and death:<note place="margin">Jer.
17.</note>
                  </q> my heart tells me (and though he be the greateſt impoſture in the world, yet you and <hi>I</hi> may beleeve him now, as you will beleeve the words of a dying man, for then hee is ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) that reformation is a kinde of killing; it is a mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a crucifying (the words ſound like Latine, more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is) a <hi>death,</hi> it defiles my <hi>Idols,</hi> it ſtarves my gods; you may ſay to him, that will reforme you indeed (nay, if the heart be not over powred then you will ſay) as the <hi>Iſraelite</hi> did, <hi>intendeſt thou to kill me?</hi> And hee will anſwer, if hee me nes to doe his offic to purpoſe, <hi>yes that he will,</hi> he will <hi>kill thee,</hi> if he can, he hath a mind to it, he will kill in me and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112349:25"/> thee, that which we call <hi>ſelfe;</hi> nay, he will deale cruelly with us, he will plucke away our gods which are as deare unto us as our right eye and arme. This is a <hi>killing a death</hi> ſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.<note place="margin">1 King. 22</note> Truely the heart is ſo contrary to it, to reformation <hi>I</hi> meane, as the bad King was to the honeſt Prophet (one againſt foure hundred) the heart hateth it and will oppoſe it, while it hath a being in it ſelfe: why? for ſaith the heart, Reformation intends no good concerning mee but evill: (though indeed it intends nothing but good to me.) For it would defile my <hi>Idols,</hi> and ſtarve my
<hi>Gods,</hi> but that is a death, <hi>I</hi> can no more heare of it than
<hi>Pilat</hi> could, what <hi>truth was,</hi> he asked the queſtion,
<hi>what is truth?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 18.38.</note> and turned his backe upon it, not ſtaying the anſwer, and ſo did moſt contrary to
<hi>truth,</hi> ſo will the heart doe: The heart may aske, <hi>what is Reformation, what is it to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ile an Idoll?</hi> But the <hi>heart</hi> will not abide the anſwer. <hi>I</hi> would be underſtood in this point, and that a child in underſtanding might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If</hi> reformation comes towards the heart, it ſeemes to march <hi>furiouſly</hi> like <hi>Jehu,</hi> ſlaſhing and killing where it comes as if it would not ſpare any one <hi>Image</hi> or <hi>Image</hi> ſerver, <hi>It</hi> will caſt downe all the Idolls before the eyes, and caſt out all the gods out of the heart. Death ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to march along with it, where it comes, for it takes away all life from the courſe of the world, wherein <hi>I</hi> walked: All delight from the beggerly rudiments and old cuſtomes of the times, wherein before <hi>I</hi> tooke pleaſure; it drawes forth my hand to remove the ſtumbling blocke before my eyes, and commands my heart to <hi>defile</hi> all my <hi>Idolls</hi> there, and that is a perfect death indeed; <hi>I</hi> ſay a perfect death, ſo farre as reformation is perfected; and the heart flies from it as from death, it cannot abide ſo much as to heare of it, but if it muſt heare of it and entertaine it too, then the heart welcomes it as a man takes fire into his boſome: indeed reformation comes into the world as the Lord Chriſt came, <hi>to ſend fire on the earth.</hi> It was ſo in all ages downeward to this day, it will be ſo to the end of the world:
<note place="margin">Luke 12.49.</note>
                  <hi>Behold Hee ſhall come ſaith the Lord.</hi> Who? The Lord Chriſt, what to doe? To reforme His Church,
<note place="margin">Mic. 3.1.</note>
                  <hi>He ſhall ſit as a refiner and</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:112349:26"/> 
                  <hi>Purifier of Silver.</hi> A gracious and a glorious worke; how will it be entertained? As a man welcomes fire and ſword, which muſt either purifie him or conſume him: <hi>who may abide the day of His comming? and who ſhall ſtand when Hee appeares for He is like a refiners fire and like Fullers Sope.</hi> This refining worke is a ſearching worke, and findes bad wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in the world. Looke we into the Church the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations there, upon the Prieſt and his people, how doe they fret at it, though but one foot and comming towards them, as if already <hi>cut to the very heart.</hi> But I need not looke abroad nor unto others; I will returne to my owne heart, for there I can read all this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SEGT. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>If reformation be a defiling of Idols, and the worke in hand, then a man needs not goe into the Congregations to behold the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Prieſt and people there, nor abroad to enquire, what newes? he may returne home to his owne heart, and read the newes there.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Can read the times now, what newes is moſt ſtirring, and and fitteſt to be enquired after; and yet not move one ſtep from the
<hi>Idoll</hi> and my owne <hi>heart:</hi> I can tell what is done in the great world, by looking diligently what is done in my little world. And the way I take muſt be this, I muſt read <hi>Reformation,</hi> and the proceſſes thereof, and what its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are; then I muſt reade in my owne heart how that ſtands towards it, in its naturall poſture: And behold it ſtands in a poſture of offence, nay of defiance moſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereunto. I will bring them (I had almoſt ſaid <hi>together,</hi> but that is impoſſible to man) to an interview, that we may heare how they greet one the other, what is demanded, and what denyed betwixt them. Thereby I ſhall make more then a conjecture what is done in the Kingdome, what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and contrariety of wills there.</p>
               <p>Reformation tells me, I muſt not walke according to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112349:26"/> the <hi>courſe</hi> of <hi>this world.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 2.22</note> My heart makes anſwer, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that courſe it will walke, though it be according to the ſpirit that now <hi>worketh</hi> in the <hi>Children of diſobedience:</hi> Reformation ſaith, I muſt forſake the beggerly Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and old cuſtomes, ſuch as were in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes; the heart anſwers, ſhe will not forſake them, they are her lovers, ſhe hankers after them, and after them ſhee will goe: Reformation tells me, I muſt worſhip God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as Hee hath commanded, I muſt not make a mingle mangle in Religion: I muſt not ſerve God partly as Hee hath commanded, partly according to my <hi>owne underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;</hi> I muſt not mate the wiſedome of God with my foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh conceits, my ſilly inventions. The heart anſwers ſhee likes her owne way, and would heare no more of that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for ſhe is ſetled and reſolved to ſerve God her owne way, and to maintaine that way till ſhe dies: Reformation tells me, I muſt through down the <hi>Idolls</hi> before my eyes. My heart is pretly flexible here, ſo it be but a <hi>ſtocke</hi> or a <hi>ſtone:</hi> God hath given me reaſon, &amp; I muſt ſhew my ſelfe a man, it were a ſhame to ſtumble in a Sun-ſhine, at ſtocks and ſtones.</p>
               <p>But Reformation is not contented with this. It goes on, commands me to give up my two Idolls, my <hi>eaſe,</hi> which I love ſo well: The
<hi>profit</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of the world, which I dote upon. Me thinkes I finde my heart <hi>mad upon theſe Idols,</hi> now they are demanded of me, and my <hi>two eyes</hi> ſparkle with rage; rather then I will part with them;<note place="margin">Jer. 50.38.</note> My Plate ſhall goe, and, which ſhould be more pretious, a good conſcience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: My <hi>eaſe</hi> is more then my Plate; and my credit in the world my chiefeſt Jewell. Reformation heares not, it ſtands like an upright Judge, as doth the ſtalke of a bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance. It demands as once <hi>Moſes</hi> did, All; All my gods, how pleaſing, how ſerviceable to mine owne ends, how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable ſoever; how deare or neare, no matter: I muſt yeeld them up and my ſtrong holds there (the houſe of my Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and guardians thereof) with my
<hi>Imaginations</hi> and every thing that exalteth it ſelfe.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 20.4.</note> The heart will ſticke here, nay it will die here before it will yeeld: offer the heart
<hi>faire,</hi> heaven and eternall happineſſe, it will not yeeld; offer it
<hi>foule,</hi> hell &amp; everlaſting miſery, it will not yeeld up its Idoll, he will not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112349:27"/> ſuffer it to be ſlaine before his ſtrong holds ſhall bee given up, before his <hi>reaſonings</hi> can give or take ſatisfaction. As the Lord ſaid,<note place="margin">Jer.
22.29.</note> O <hi>Earth, earth, earth,</hi> heare the Word of the Lord. It cannot heare, no more can the <hi>heart;</hi> it is <hi>deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wicked,</hi> who ſhall make a good underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and reformation? Of this in the cloſe.</p>
               <p>Now we have ſeene at what a diſtance the heart ſtands to heaven, that patterne wee are to bee conformed unto; how it fighteth to maintaine his Idols, which hee will not part with till he dyes. Then wee may eaſily gather by the unquiet motions within, what is done without; if there be ſuch motions in one mans little world, what motions will there be in Cities, in Towns, in a Kingdom, when Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſſaies to go through the ſame, to defile the Idols there? If men will fret and fume and doe more, becauſe <hi>ſtockes</hi> and <hi>ſtones</hi> are defiled; what will they doe for the Idoll in the heart, to maintaine that in a poſture of defence? If defiling of <hi>Idols</hi> in one mans heart, cauſe ſuch a ſhaking, what a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſhake will it be, when the <hi>Earth</hi> ſhall no more cover
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r blood, but the men there muſt yeeld up their <hi>Idols</hi> to the <hi>Moles</hi> and to the <hi>Batts?</hi> Reformation will caſt a ſpew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon all our worldly glory; it will defile the three gods of the world, honours, pleaſures, profits, for which the heart will contend till it die; then the moſt ſtirring newes is, <hi>warres</hi> and <hi>Rumors of warres;</hi> Saint <hi>James</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves it ſo; whence comes warres and fightings amongſt you, even of the luſts, which war in your members. There they warre firſt, then they breake forth in the world. If we could open the records of all ages, and then put Saint <hi>James</hi> his queſtion; we muſt alſo make his anſwer, our owne winds, the windes from within us make our Sea ſo tempeſtuous: The counſell is good, <hi>calme it with your Prayers,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to throw out your Idoll;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fluctus maris tuis precibusmi tiga, Hier. Ep.</hi> 45. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> But that worke will cauſe a mightie contention. While there is a Divell in Hell, a Prince in the Ayer, a partie on earth, and a king over them, which is the Angell of the bottomleſſe pit, ſo long Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will find a mightie oppoſition, what the gates of Hell can make.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:112349:27"/> And if Reformation be ſo oppoſed, as that which deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth defileth <hi>Idolls,</hi> then it is quickly read, how reformers are accounted of.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.9,10.</note>
                  <hi>The thing that hath beene, it is that which ſhall be; and that which is done, is that which ſhall be done, and there is no new thing under the Sunne. Is there any thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it may be ſaid, See, this is new? It hath beene already of old time, which was before us.</hi> They that have beene employed in Temple-worke, and in defiling of <hi>Idols,</hi> they have ever beene accounted factious, ſeditious, rebellious, thoſe that would turne the <hi>world upſide downe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 17.6.</note> I muſt adde (&amp;c.) for there is a great deale more:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 59.6. <hi>Exulem me de ſuo nomine vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Cicer. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratox.</hi> Jer. 9.8. 2 King. 9.24. Matth. 10.25.</note> yet we read all in theſe words, <hi>Behold they belch out with their mouth;</hi> what are their words? very <hi>Swords are in their lippes,</hi> they would ſlay the righteous man therewith, for they call him <hi>by their owne name,</hi> and that is a devouring name, as bad as can be; <hi>their tongue is as an arrow ſhot-out,</hi> which malice ever drawes to the very head, as
<hi>Jehu</hi> drew his bow with his full ſtrength. But none of all that is ſtrange: The righteous are not troubled at it, their patience can digeſt more then this; beſides, their Lord and maſter hath beene ſo reproached, and <hi>If they have called the Maſter of the Houſe Belzebub, How much more ſhall they call them of his houſhold?</hi> But what ſhall we thinke? Can Reformation goe on? Shall <hi>Idols</hi> be defiled even now? Shall theſe Refiners proſper? There is ſome reſolution given hereunto, as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding the contempt that is caſt upon Reformation and Reformers, yet both ſhall goe on and proſper.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Will beginne with Queſtions and Anſwers. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Shall this worke of defiling Images, (for that I call Reformation) ſhall it goe on?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes ſure, God wills and commands Images to be defiled, and it muſt be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> At this time?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:112349:28"/> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There I am at a ſtand, I cannot certainly tell that; I thinke ſo, but in Gods time it ſhall be done, which time, the <hi>Father</hi> hath put in His owne power.<note place="margin">Acts 1.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But the righteous, they that walke in the truth, that <hi>doe faithfully whatſoever they doe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 Joh. 3.4.</note> may ſay as their Brethron be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, <hi>our worke is Reproached and we are deſpiſed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 4 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>They may ſay ſo indeed, but it is a very good ſigne, that the worke goes on, Idols ſhall be defiled even now. It is, I ſay as comfortable a ſigne as can be wiſhed; the divell and his party have
<hi>great wrath,</hi> therefore wee know they have <hi>but a ſhort time.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel 12.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But in a ſhort time they may doe a
<hi>length</hi> of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> True, but they are held ſhort in a chaine, which the Lord holds in His hand, and they cannot proceed an inch farther, then He lets it forth: And a great good ſigne it is, they ſhall not proceed much farther becauſe the Almightie hath them in His fetters. And they feele themſelves checkt and curbed-in as a wilde bull in a net. But they thinke their tongue is their owne, and at liberty, therefore they ſay as once they did;</p>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> What doe theſe men? will <hi>they fortifie themſelves?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 4 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> Yes, that they will, <hi>in the Lord and power of His might,</hi> for <hi>wiſedome</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> are
<hi>His;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 6.10.</note> And He is a good Lord, a
<hi>ſtrong hold in the day of trouble, and He knoweth them that truſt in Him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 2.20.</note> The adverſary mocks on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> Will <hi>they make an end in a day?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nahum
1.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> No, nor in a yeare neither;
<note place="margin">Neh. 4 2.</note> Temple worke, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing of Idols there goes on more ſlowly then <hi>Romes</hi> work doth; yet we know the proverbe, and that <hi>Romes</hi> Leaven hath not ſowred the whole lumpe yet; and experience tels us, that the heires of the beard or head wax not white alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. One Idoll is ſmitten now, another to morrow, in good time, they ſhall all be defiled. The adverſary goes on much caſt downe (as formerly)
<hi>in their owne eyes, for they perceive, that the worke</hi> (now alſo as then) <hi>is wrought of our God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 6.16</note> and is ſo firme and ſtable, that a <hi>Fox</hi> cannot break it downe with all his cunning, they muſt adde the ſtrength
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:112349:28"/> of a Lyon to it too, and therein is their hope.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> That theſe <hi>feeble men</hi> ſhall not be able to goe on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> Thus the adverſary reproached anciently the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord, who went on the better and more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably: though indeed they were then, and are now but a <hi>feeble folke;</hi> ſo are the Conies <hi>too, yet make they their houſes in the rockes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 30.26.</note> A feeble folke that have the <hi>munition of Rockes</hi> for their defence; and a Redeemer <hi>that ſainteth not, nor is weary;</hi> They may doe great things: for Hee is <hi>mightie and ſtrong; The Lord of Hoſts is His name, He ſhall throughly plead His cauſe, That He may give reſt to the Land, and diſquiet the inhabitants of Babilon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 33.16. 40.26.</note> Againe, we ſay their ſtrength may well be waſted in all this time; but they have a continuall influence and ſupply from the Spring head, the God of their ſtrength, to whom they have a continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe:<note place="margin">Jer.
50.34.</note> for as the waters neare them run from the fountain every morning and returne to it every night; ſo doe they receive from God and returne to God: ſo they renew their ſtrength like Eagles, and goe from ſtrength to ſtrength with the increaſe of God; for as was ſayd, when they be at a low ebbe, then they flow upward to their fountaine and ſpring head; whereas theſe <hi>ſcorners</hi> are like waters wee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve running from the ſpring head and never returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; and they are <hi>feeble</hi> men indeed, but let them ſay what they have deviſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> That theſe feeble men ſhall not be able to carry on the work, and beare up any longer againſt the tide of oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and contradiction of tongues; ſo ſome ſay and vaunt too and good men feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> I will anſwer firſt as Maſter <hi>Jewell</hi> (whoſe face did ſhine in every mans eye but his owne) in a caſe, not unlike,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad certu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> ſunt Chriſtian, poſtea per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t, &amp; redibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Idola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit quo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>rae autea Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> tu cum expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctas, miſer infidelis, ut tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Christiani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> trauſis ipſe ſine Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianis. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</hi> In Pſal. 70. See <hi>Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l.</hi> pag. 26.</note>
                  <q rend="inline">"I have no skill ſaith bee in the wicked mans,
<hi>Almanack,</hi> Gods will be done. It is His cauſe whatſoever ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and His Name be bleſſed for ever for what He hath done. But ſo vaunted the heathen againſt the <hi>faith</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Theſe Chriſtians are but for a while, fall they ſhall and that ſhortly: Then ſhall our <hi>Idols</hi> come againe, and it ſhall be as it was before. But, O thou miſerable Infidell, while thou lookeſt that the Chriſtians ſhould paſſe, thou
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112349:29"/> paſſeſt away thy ſelfe without the Chriſtians.</q> This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit is like that of the country foole, who comming to a quicke running ſtreame, thought verily the water would ſoone paſſe by, and hee might paſſe over anon on foote, not conſidering that the ſtreame was continually fed from the ſpring-head. Maſter <hi>Jewell</hi> goes on and reades out of <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruſticus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectat dum defluat a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>abitur, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>abetur in om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e volu bilis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> l.</hi>
1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Ecce ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> pus.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ani Sic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t caeperunt ad
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>quo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>pore, ita uſque ad cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m pus erant. Sed cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riantur, &amp; perm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Eccleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a praedicans
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> venturae.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <q rend="inline">"They ſay behold, the day will come, when all theſe Chriſtians ſhall have an end; as they had a time to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, ſo ſhall they have a time to continue. But while they make theſe crackes, they themſelves die without end. But the Church continueth ſtill, prayſing the Almighty arme of God to every generation that is to come.</q> The appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is full and eaſie.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe now, that the worke ſhould ſtop and ceaſe, as the Temple-worke did, for ſome yeares; and the Church ſhould have her
<hi>Idols</hi> againe, from which (the Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us) we are not cleanſed to this day. So farre wicked counſellers may prevaile as they did in former time. What then? yet notwithſtanding the <hi>Reformers</hi> have not
<hi>laboured in vaine, nor ſpent their ſtrength for nought and in vaine</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Eſa. 49.4.</note>. It is a comfortable ſpeech;
<q rend="inline">"There is no ſervice that is done to the Lord but ſhall have its due and ſeaſonable recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence,</q> 
                  <hi>Whatſoever good thing any man doth, the ſame ſhall hee receive</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 6.7,8. Ezek. 29.18,19.</note>. <hi>Mordecay</hi> was remembred, and in the fitteſt ſeaſon, ſo were <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and his brethren <hi>remembred for good.</hi> Temple-worke is an acceptable worke; and they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file Idols doe according to Gods owne heart; And ſhall not that ſervice be remembred? Judge you: <hi>Babels</hi> King ſhall not <hi>ſerve a great ſervice</hi> for nought. The Lord put that King upon the ſervice againſt <hi>Tirus,</hi> and Hee paid Him wages for His <hi>Army:</hi> and if the Lord be Paymaſter, Hee will pay like Himſelfe, the wages ſhall be no leſſe then a Kingdome. <hi>Woe unto him that uſeth his neighbours ſervice without wages, and giveth him not for his worke.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 22.13.</note> Doth the Lord pronounce this woe? Then certainly He will not uſe any faithfull mans ſervice without wages: Hee will give him for his worke, and better payment then <hi>Babels</hi> King had; yet that was a Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:112349:29"/> Indeed, it is very comfortable for them that
<hi>ſerve</hi> a great <hi>Service</hi> for the Church of Chriſt. Surely their ſervice ſhall not be forgotten, for they have done it as to the Lord, and not unto men. Therefore they have a ſtronger conſolation then all this; that which containes all, they have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of God, the ſame with which the Lord Himſelfe was comforted. They can ſay as their Lord did, though <hi>Iſrael</hi> be not reformed, though her Idols be not defiled at this time, <hi>yet ſurely our judgement is with the Lord, and our worke with our God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 49.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we have concluded what ever falls out, though things goe backe as the Adverſary would have it, and our ſinnes doe deſerve. It is a point of good diſcretion, <hi>as to wiſh the beſt, ſo to forecaſt the worſt and to prepare to beare what ever commeth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro tua ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebis optare optima, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitare dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficilima, ferre quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Cic. Ep. fam. L.</hi>
9.19.</note> yet ſtill holding to the concluſion of experience, that it ſhall bee well with them that ſerve the Lorld, their recompence is ſure.</p>
               <p>When we looke up, fixing our eye where we ſhould, our hopes exceed our feares, and we conclude, that the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation muſt goe on; He that hath wrought hitherto, will worke, Hee that brought them onward ſo farre, will not leave them within ſight of the promiſed Land; Hee that hath protected will protect ſtill, and uphold with the hand. Though yet, as
<hi>Luther</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.2.</note>
                  <q rend="inline">"when we are reforming our ſelves or others, and defiling Idols, the divell overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſometimes. Why? for our advantage every way, that we may have the experience of a ſtronger againſt that ſtrong one,</q> and may ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, when I am weake then am I ſtrong,</hi> we will then ſpeake confidently, <hi>the Reformers ſhall goe on and proſper,</hi> for;</p>
               <p>They are in the <hi>Worke,</hi> in the <hi>Way,</hi> in the
<hi>Hand</hi> of the Lord:</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the worke, and they <hi>wrought with God this day.</hi> Reforming worke is Gods worke, as we heard.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are in Gods way; this is His way, He lets in a cleare light into the ſoule: firſt, He diſcovers, He manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſt there; then the Idolls are caſting out and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: This is their way alſo, they labour with all their might
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112349:30"/> to exalt Chriſt, then the Idols fall and are defiled: when the ſoule comes to ſee the excelling beautie of Jeſus Chriſt, the glory of the world is darkeneſſe to her; but Idols are as a
<hi>monſtruous cloth.</hi> Againe, in Gods way ſtill, He began at the Sanctuary, ſo did they; and did they make cleane worke there, did they carry forth the <hi>filthineſſe</hi> thence, ſurely things would goe on;<note place="margin">2 Chro. 29 5.</note> but they are in Gods way He purifies the ſonnes of <hi>Levi,</hi> Sanctuary men, ſo doe they. But they will not be purged; No, then they muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, chooſe they whether. Either the Idoll muſt be left or the ſoule muſt be loſt, there is but one way: Ah but they ſhall never goe on in that way; <hi>Sorcerers, Adulterers, falſe ſwcarers, oppreſſors</hi> (to ſumme up all) and thoſe that <hi>feare not. Me ſaith the Lord;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.5.</note> What all theſe doutie men can doe ſhall be done as in ancient dayes, in way of oppoſition to this worke, and to keepe their Idols in a poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. True, but that which followes now will be too hard for them all, for;</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are in Gods hand; There is ſecuritie againſt all might and power whatſoever; there they may be merry in the Lord, laugh and rejoyce. As <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, when the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſet themſelves againſt him, and the people raged, now ſaith he, <hi>the Lord laugheth, I am not ſuch a foole as to cry:</hi> his meaning was (for there is a figure) he would <hi>laugh</hi> too, and being merry, hee would ſing the 46. Pſalme. Theſe ſervants of the Lord may laugh alſo, and for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. They are in Gods hand, a good, a gracious, an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie hand; that is the confidence: five hundred men cannot plucke one man thence. They will
<hi>hold faſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb 3.6.</note> This Hand brought them together at firſt, hath kept them ever ſince, hath proſpered them to this time: can they caſt away their confidence now? No, they know whom they have truſted; He will keepe them as the Apple of His eye; they have borne the burthen and heate of the day: the wicked ſhall not receive the wages. They have ſought God for this thing, and have ſowen in teares, the wicked ſhall not reape in joy; ſurely they ſay,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.42.</note>
                  <hi>The Lord will not ſet up the right hand of His adverſaries; He will not make</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:112349:30"/> 
                  <hi>His enemies to rejoyce.</hi> This is their confidence now; ſo though the kingdomes are moved, yet they may <hi>be ſtill</hi> calme and quiet in their minds, for ſo they are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;
<hi>Be ſtill:</hi> what and the Kingdomes moved?<note place="margin">Pſal.
46.10</note> What can ſtill the ſpirit then? this; <hi>Know</hi> (that is, truſt perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <hi>that I am God, and I will be exalted, &amp;c.</hi> It is an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſervation, that all the Letters in <hi>Jehovah</hi> are
<hi>quieſcent i. e.</hi> doe import <hi>quietneſſe</hi> and
<hi>reſt;</hi> it is of lively uſe. I deſire not ſo much to looke upon bare Letters as the Name it ſelfe, the <hi>goodneſſe, mercy, wiſedome, power of God;</hi> and behold there the ſoule can finde reſt and ſweet repoſe when there is <hi>terrour on every ſide;</hi> when Kingdomes are moved, the earth quakes, then there is reſt: Where? In God. O
<hi>bleſſedneſſes,</hi> compleatly bleſſed is the man, that can ſay, and knoweth what he ſaith, <hi>The Lord is my God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.</note> He reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, be the earth never ſo unquiet, yet He is King, and will be exalted.</p>
               <p>When there is an Earthquake, and we looke for it; when not the winds, but the Lord will ſhake it, ſmiting it <hi>terribly,</hi> then, in ſuch a trembling time, this man is as the Lord hath promiſed to make his people, a <hi>quiet habitation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 33.29.</note> Who would not be as He is? Who would not reſt as he doth? in the armes, and under the ſhadow of the Almighty? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every man. Surely then, if he would be aſſured and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, he muſt give up his gods; hee muſt yeeld up their ſtrong holds, but this muſt be more fully conſidered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Every man muſt returne to his owne heart, and enquire dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently the means of reconciliation, and reſolve upon yeelding up the Idoll.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>REformation and the heart ſtand at a wide diſtance, as we heard; there muſt be a yeelding, ſo as they may be brought together.
<hi>Reformation</hi> cannot yeeld, it is ſtiffe as was the Heathens god, made of the ſame matter the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:112349:31"/> make theirs, which they called
<hi>Terminus,</hi> wee call it a <hi>Bound-ſtone,</hi> the <hi>old Land-marke, cedebat nulli,</hi> it would not yeeld an inch for any mans pleaſure;
<note place="margin">Prov. 23.10. <hi>Aug. de Civit.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 4.23. 2 Sam
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Reformation is as ſtiffe, it will yeeld nothing, not a <hi>hooſe,</hi> not a <hi>huske,</hi> not ſuch a poore matter as was a <hi>piece of ground full of Lentiles;</hi> It was not a conſiderable <hi>piece.</hi> What though? yet the
<hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims</hi> ſhould not have it. So ſtiffe is Reformation in yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to any thing againſt Gods right. And great reaſon it ſhould be ſo, why ſhould it yeeld that which is anothers? God gives all, He muſt have all, all the <hi>heart,</hi> and all the <hi>ſoule,</hi> and all the
<hi>mind.</hi> Indeed Reformation can yeeld nothing; It commands in Gods name, and will have all its Demands, the heart muſt bow and ſubmit, or periſh for ever. As the Lord ſaid to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 15
19.</note> 
                  <hi>let them returne unto thee:</hi> But <hi>returne not thou unto them:</hi> That is, they muſt yeeld to thy termes, thou ſhalt not yeeld to theirs. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation hath the ſame charge from the Lord, and is as peremptory in her demands. And now it will be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the whole world, that the heart is as it is ſaid to be, deceitfull above all things, <hi>and deſperatly wicked.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 17 19.</note> It appeares thus;</p>
               <p>The ſoule is the moſt pretious thing in the world, never any thing came up to the price of it, but the blood of God, He gave to the full worth, for He gave Himſelfe.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.4.</note> What is an Idoll now? Nothing, <hi>We know that an Idoll is nothing in the world,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>or if any thing, then, as hee hath ſaid, That ſhame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 11.13.</note> A goodly price that our ſoules are prized at by us; below thirtie peeces of Silver, and no wonder. For ſo the Lord Chriſt was prized. But yet wee muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how
<hi>deſperatly wicked</hi> the heart is. Reformation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires no more but the giving up the Idoll, with the ſtrong hold (the <hi>forme</hi> without the
<hi>power</hi>) which maintaines it. See now! the heart will not yeeld; it will venture an eternall ſoule, the everlaſtaing well-being thereof, rather than it will yeeld up its Idols: It is ſetled and reſolved to keepe his enmitie, to maintaine a defiance, it will hold it out till it die; though if I would
<hi>quickly, while I am in the way</hi> with him, agree with this
<hi>adverſary, Reformation</hi> I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112349:31"/> meane, and upon its owne termes and conditions, it would be the happieſt agreement that could be made; for then the Idoll, which troubled my peace all my life long, will be thruſt out, and my Lord would come in, and with Him all things.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paenitentiam mihi praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, ſed talis ſum ego mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, &amp; quod ſentio me</hi> Nolle <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> poſſe, <hi>quare tuis poſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis pelibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>cio de paenitentia Anno Dom.</hi>
1518.</note> But this is a worke I neither <hi>will</hi> doe nor <hi>can</hi> doe: I can ſtand it out ſtoutly, I can <hi>hold faſt</hi> the
<hi>forme</hi> onely, and that will <hi>hold faſt</hi> my Idoll; I am ſtubbornely bent to maintaine warre and all my ſtrong-holds: But to make a good agreement and underſtanding betwixt <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and my
<hi>heart:</hi> To yeeld to the Demands there, and ſo to bring Reformation and my heart together, is as impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to me, as to make the North and South meet as friends, and to kiſſe each other, which ſtand as wee heard, at an eternall oppoſition. But with God all things are poſſible: <hi>His Word runneth very ſwiftly, He ſent forth His Commandement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 147.15.</note> and it was done, <hi>Let there be light, and there was light, Let there be a firmament, and it was ſo.</hi> Nay, He hath done a more aſtoniſhing worke then all this: Hee hath made
<hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> to meet, and kiſſe each other: He hath filled up that gulfe betwixt us, and made it paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Hee hath brought two together, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> and hath cauſed a good underſtanding betwixt them: So as they are no longer two now, but one
<hi>Immanuel:</hi> Then He can do what He pleaſeth, therefore my eye muſt bee to Him, Who onely doth wonders; And it is every mans worke who knowes his dutie, for ſurely we have no might againſt this great company of gods, which are within us and fight againſt us, neither can we over-power our owne hearts. But if our eyes are upon the Lord: If we ſet our ſelves as one man to ſeeke Him, wee ſhall finde that there is hope in <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning this thing: for the King of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> is a mercifull King, heare what He ſaith;
<note place="margin">Jer. 3.1.</note>
                  <hi>thou haſt play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the harlot with many lovers: yet returne againe to Me ſaith the Lord: My righteouſneſſe is neere: my ſalvation is gone forth, and mine armes ſhall judge the people.</hi> What then? Then <hi>the Iſles ſhall waite upon Me, and on my Arme ſhall they truſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay
51.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It is time to recall my ſelfe now, though I doe not find
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:112349:32"/> I have digreſſed: I have beene upon the
<hi>defiling</hi> of Images and their <hi>Ornament,</hi> which is the hardeſt worke in the world; if it hath taken up more ſpace here then was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected it could have done, it was that it might take up more roome in the heart.</p>
               <p>I muſt remember, I am cloſing the treatiſe, which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe, before I have reſolved according to my promiſe, a ſecond doubt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The heart deceives us in point of Ornament; that which muſt be defiled, is but in Name ſo: The Citie, in place of an Idoll will raiſe up a <hi>Pillar,</hi> and write thereon the former yeares deliverances. Concerning this preſent yeare there is a great queſtion, wherein ſhee will be reſolved in the next Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>MAn is much miſtaken in point of Ornament: that which he counts pleaſant to his eyes, and to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, defiles him, and muſt be defiled. But it is our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and more, I may ſay our
<hi>Death;</hi> that we account that an <hi>Ornament,</hi> which is our
<hi>ſhame:</hi> if that be taken from us, our <hi>Idol</hi> I meane, or an offer made that way, we are ready to whine, and can ſay almoſt as he did, and <hi>what have I more?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 18.24.</note> O the darkeneſſe that is in our minds! The vaile ſpread over our hearts, not yet taken away, but of this enough. And yet, O that a deceived heart might beguile us no longer! It was a good anſwer the man of God gave
<hi>Amaziah,</hi> making queſtion about the Talents, <hi>the Lord is able to give thee much more then this;</hi> more then our <hi>eaſe,</hi> that will ſlay us:<note place="margin">2 Chro. 25.9.</note> More then our
<hi>Bargaine</hi> for a penny a day, that will prove but poore wages, though it be a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke. More then the <hi>glory</hi> of this world, for a cloud
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:112349:32"/> will come and overſhadow it.
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.10. Heb. 12.28.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> from
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuo, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in Salo ſeu mariſtans.</hi>
                  </note> More then Kingdomes here below, which have no
<hi>foundations;</hi> or if any, then like that foundation the foote hath ſtanding upon the waters: Therefore theſe muſt bee <hi>ſhaken</hi> as the kingdomes before them, which have beene ſhaken and broken to pieces, but the Kingdome of Heaven <hi>cannot be ſhaken:</hi> Wee cannot but know all this, if wee will ſhew our ſelves men. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the <hi>Idoll</hi> fall, let his <hi>Ornament</hi> be. defiled, whether without and before the eye, or within the houſe of my ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary; let it goe, and bee defiled, the Lord can give us <hi>much more,</hi> a <hi>Peace</hi> which may be interrupted, but can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be taken away. A <hi>glory</hi> which may be eclipſed here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but ſhall ſhine forth to all eternitie; <hi>An inheritance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in heaven.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I would ſharpen this point, and make it keene in the heart of the Idols, the Kings enemies and ours. Let us then aske our ſelves this queſtion ſeriouſly, ſoberly and ſadly, <hi>Is it peace?</hi> We muſt then make anſwer, <hi>What peace?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King.
9.22.</note> So long as our Idolls are ſo many. It is a concluſion of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience as ancient as the time, when man was firſt created upon the earth; <hi>That falſe gods, and a true peace could never ſtand together:</hi> If they be entertained, the true God will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, conſider wee then of the matter, and then make our choyſe.</p>
               <p>Is not the preſence of God more then the preſence of ten Idolls? Is not He an Ornament? the beautie of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe? Is not His grace the Ornament of beautie? Let our Idoll goe, and this God will come, elſe not; for what agreement betwixt Him and Idols? But if they goe out, He comes in; A good Exchange and as full of comfort; our wonder will be why we did not yeeld ſooner: why we maintained warre ſo long, ſo long loved death; why wee were ſo unwilling to let in Peace; and ſo way is made to give full ſatisfaction to the doubt (what they ſhall doe for an Ornament?) and to the heart of the Citie.</p>
               <p>The Croſſes good friends and neighbours doe pine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Idoll; and they demand of me;
<q rend="inline">"if the Croſſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112349:33"/> muſt be taken away, and the
<hi>Ornament</hi> of the Images de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed alſo</q> (which upon due conſideration of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, the ſtouteſt adverſary in the world dares not deny) <hi>What then ſhall be done for the Cities ornament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. That which is fully to the minde of the Citie, and to the heart of the righteous there: The greateſt Reaſon in the world, that a Citie ſo famous; that hath done ſo worthily, quitted her ſelfe ſo like her ſelfe; hath ſo magnified her office, hath ſtood up for God, for His truth obove all the Cities in the world; great reaſon, I ſay that this Citie ſhould have an <hi>Ornament:</hi> ſhe may expect to be dealt with nobly and honorably at this point; ſo ſhe ſhall be, &amp; be put to her owne choyce, and then we know what ſhe will chooſe. She will prepare a
<hi>Pillar</hi> &amp; write upon it, how the Lord hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fooled his adverſaries the former yeare: how He was above them in all, wherein they
<hi>dealt proudly,</hi> breaking yoakes and ſnares, and turning the wiſedome of <hi>Achitophell</hi> into Fooliſhneſſe;<note place="margin">Exod. 18.11.</note> how He magnified His free grace; exalted His right hand; did valiantly; was glorious in wiſedome, triumphed in power, was marvailous in working, when He cauſed His people to paſſe <hi>under the rod ſo brought them into the bond of the Covenant.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> Then they will write the Biſhops warre (ſo they called it) the beginning, the progreſſe, the cloſe, all is wonderfull. All the Chronicles in the world, Hebrew, Greeke, Latine, Engliſh, &amp;c. cannot yeeld us a ſtory which will run paralell with this; That two great armies came from their places, ſtared each other in the face for ſome moneths together, and ſo ſtood in open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance one againſt another in as great a contrarietie of wills and affections each to other, as are the Angells in heaven to the Devils in hell: and yet before the yeare was up, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned backe to backe, and ſo departed without ſhedding one drop of blood betwixt them. O wonderfull! yes truly.
<note place="margin">Ezech. 23.32.</note> But the wonder muſt be raiſed higher yet; that a people <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> againſt,
<hi>exclaimed</hi> againſt, <hi>proclaimed</hi> enemies, rebells, &amp;c. for it <hi>containes much,</hi> ſhould in the ſame place and time of the yeare, be <hi>prayed</hi> for in our Congregations, bee <hi>ſtiled</hi> and
<hi>enacted</hi> our <hi>Brethren, loyall, faithfull</hi> ſubjects to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:112349:33"/> God and their King; ſo they were indeed, O wonderfull yeare that! workes of a God, who onely doth wonders.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Touching this preſent yeare, a Doctor tells us, that God hath done little or nothing for his Church; but rather much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her. The Preachers <hi>concluſion</hi> and <hi>reſpects</hi> are weighed at the Sanctuary and found light: And a <hi>concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> contrary thereunto is ſet downe, and proved to be in divers <hi>reſpects</hi> agreeable to the mind of God and underſtanding of the Godly.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THis will ſuffice for the former yeare, and fill up two Columnes of the Pillar. But what hath the Lord done for His people this preſent yeare, which may now be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded with rejoycing We muſt anſwer, what ever adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary or friend ſaith to the contrary, <hi>Great things:</hi> therefore muſt the Citie continue the Records; for behold mercies after mercies, and loving kindneſſes have followed loving kindneſſes as the waves of the Sea. It is asked, where are they? for hearke what a great Clerke ſaith, and a Maſter in Iſrael;
<q rend="inline">"<hi>Things are as they were, nay much worſe, refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of corruptions hath beene endeavoured with much zeale and diligence,</hi> yet the end not attained. Nay, in ſome <hi>reſpects</hi> it is ſo farre ſet backe, that in my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the ſtate of Religion hath never beene worſe ſince the firſt reformation, then this preſent yeare. What reſpects? theſe follow, in reſpect of, firſt, the greatneſſe of deſtractions, which have divided us all, one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then,</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">"Secondly, multitude of Sects and Sectaries, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline"> Thirdly, diſhonours done to the ſervice of God, with ſo much ſcorne and ſcandall to Religion, that in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne parts, they queſtion whether all this time we have had <hi>any,</hi> ſo abruptly he breakes off.</q> Upon eaſie ſearch we may finde theſe words towards the end of a Sermon
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:112349:34"/> printed very lately at <hi>Cambridge.</hi> I muſt ponder them whether they hold weight at the Sanctuary, whether the Doctor ſpeake according to his charge, as the <hi>Oracles of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.11</note> I ſay, I muſt doe it, for it is much againſt my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to fill up this yeare with Ciphers, to make it a
<hi>Leape yeare,</hi> as if God had done nothing this yeare worthy to be written upon the <hi>Pillar,</hi> the Citie ſtands charged to raiſe up now to the glory of her God. We take then a ſecond view of the Doctors words, he ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Obj.</hi>
                     </note>"Notwithſtanding the <hi>much zeale</hi> [of our <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>worthies</hi> he meanes] and <hi>diligence,</hi> things are much worſe then they were.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note>Here is a confuſion indeed, for here is <hi>much zeale</hi> and as <hi>much diligence,</hi> and yet things <hi>much worſe.</hi> I hope things are but in an appearance ſo, but I anſwer the <hi>much zeale</hi> firſt; (where that is there will be much diligence) I will be pretty confident the Doctor doth not fault the
<hi>zeale</hi> as <hi>too much:</hi> But as the man of God, a <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> and <hi>Seer</hi> in Iſrael, greatly affected with the Houſe and Cauſe of his God, hee would have commended the reformers zeale the more, if it had beene much more, more hot and boyling againſt the <hi>light Prophets, and treacherous Prieſts,</hi> their Idols and Idoll ſervices.</p>
               <p>That is his <hi>meaning</hi> we hope, and we muſt deale tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therewith, as with the <hi>eye</hi> and <hi>conſcience,</hi> and give the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt interpretation thereof;
<q rend="inline">"That it grieves him to the heart, that the ſucceſſe anſwers not; that the end is not attained, the
<hi>filthineſſe</hi> is not carried out of the Temple, nor are thoſe Prieſts caſt out thence, nor are their <hi>Idols defiled.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But touching all this, he can conſider and comfort him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in theſe words, That as God hath accepted a zeale for the building of His houſe, though nothing was done there: ſo will He accept <hi>much zeale</hi> for the reformation of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions there, though the end bee not preſently attained.<note place="margin">1 King. 8.18.</note> Surely the Lord takes it kindly that it was in the hearts of the reformers to do yet more for Gods houſe, and to ſhew <hi>much zeale</hi> there; Let reformers quit themſelves in point
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:112349:34"/> of <hi>zeale</hi> and <hi>deligence,</hi> that they have laboured in ſingleneſſe of affection, and uprightnes of heart, then, though their end ſhould faile, and the time ſhould be deferred, yet they ſhall not faile of comfort.
<q rend="inline">"Men muſt part their care ſo, as to take upon them onely the care of dutie, and leave the reſt to God. They muſt make good their ends, and the meanes they have uſed, in confident aſſurance; that God will make good the iſſue, and turne all to the beſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And this is a comfortable conſideration even now for they that have given <hi>all diligence</hi> about Temple worke, have not lived to ſee the end attained. And hee that had ſhewed much zeale there, thought verily, that his very zeale for God and His houſe would occaſion his death. Good man! he thought himſelfe <hi>left alone</hi> upon the earth; and O that his good Lord, for whom hee was ſo jealous, would take away his life, and not leave his <hi>ſoule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Lions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 19.</note> for them to teare the Cawle of his heart, ſo diſmaid and heartleſſe have good men beene ſometimes, when they have beene upon Temple-worke, contending for God, againſt <hi>Baall</hi> and his <hi>Prieſts.</hi> But note wee this here; That never any man, from that time to this day, did comment upon <hi>Elijahs</hi> zeale, ſaying; <hi>It was too much, and he was ſerved in his kind, that would contend with Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and beare up againſt winde and tide.</hi> No man was ſo mad, and left of his wits, and deſtitute of underſtanding, that would blame the Prophets <hi>much zeale</hi> and
<hi>diligence</hi> for God and His Houſe, when he was in his fainting fits. No; There is no other uſe of all this, but that which the Apoſtle makes for the comfort of all thoſe, that have much zeale, and are jealous for the Lord of Hoſts; <hi>Caſt not away therefore your confidence, which hath great recompence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. For yee have need of Patience, that after you have done the will of God, ye might receive the promiſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb.
10.35,36.</note> This is the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall</hi> Reformers muſt take, after they have taken much paines, and have beene very jealous for the Lord God of Hoſts, when yet things in appearance ſeeme much worſe.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place, I muſt anſwer thoſe men, who may be charitable men too, &amp; yet not acquainted with the Doctors Zeale about
<hi>Cloyſters</hi> and <hi>Cloyſter-men,</hi> thoſe <hi>Abbies</hi> and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:112349:35"/> 
                  <hi>Abby-lubbers</hi> who <hi>eate the fat, and drinke the ſweet,</hi> caring for the body onely, and no farther, what betides to the precious ſoules: I ſay, not acquainted with the <hi>Man</hi> and his known <hi>zeale,</hi> concerning theſe <hi>places</hi> and
<hi>perſons,</hi> they may read the Doctors words backwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, as if the <hi>much zeale</hi> of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes grieved the Doctor more then the <hi>end not attained.</hi> And that is it which pincheth others alſo, and ſo they lay the blame upon <hi>much zeale</hi> that things are worſe &amp; worſe. To theſe men I anſwer, <hi>I hope not ſo;</hi> things doe but ſeeme ſo to be, in a worſe condition then formerly, but ſuppoſe they are ſo, ſhall we blame Reformation or Reformers for this their <hi>much zeale</hi> and diligence? God forbid. If ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bee any want, as ſure there is in the beſt man living, it is want of zeale, and of double diligence
<hi>for the ſervice of God,</hi> which we ſhall never call the
<hi>Liturgy;</hi> The want, if any, is this; that they have not wrought through worke in Temple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, and for the cauſe of God. That they have not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out the <hi>filthineſſe</hi> out of the temple (which is the prime and chiefe worke ever) and caſt out thoſe <hi>light</hi> and
<hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous</hi> Prieſts out thence, who have <hi>polluted</hi> the
<hi>Sanctuary, and have done violence to the Law,</hi> that is all the want, which is, want of zeale, not too much zeale.<note place="margin">Zeph.
3.4.</note> Be it knowne unto the world that theſe Reformers cannot bee too zealous, though <hi>exceeding</hi> zealous: for the Lord hath beene to them
<hi>exceeding</hi> gratious; and the adverſary is <hi>exceeding</hi> proud, and the Churches friends <hi>exceeding</hi> cold; the Churches ſtraights are
<hi>exceeding</hi> great; the Prieſts and their ſervices have been, and are
<hi>exceeding</hi> abominable; and the <hi>zeale</hi> of Church-men
<hi>exceeding</hi> cold, I ſayd not well there, <hi>zeale</hi> cannot be cold; I meane, theſe Church-men for the moſt part have no <hi>zeale</hi> at all for God, but their zeale <hi>boyleth</hi> and runnes over againſt God,
<hi>and thoſe pleaſant offerings</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.4.</note> which God hath commanded, muſt and will have when all is done. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt Reformers now ſuffer themſelves (if they will ſhew themſelves in any proportion anſwerable) to be eaten up with an Holy zeale for the houſe and houſhold of God; The greatneſſe of the provocation; the excellency of the object; the weight of the occaſion beares out the ſoule, not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:112349:35"/> onely without blame (unleſſe from wicked and vile men) but with great praiſe in ſuch extaſies of zeale, ſeeming di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Rom. 12.11. <hi>Non am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t qui non Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lat. Aug.</hi>
                  </note> It is the glory of a Chriſtian to be <hi>boyling in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> to be carried with full ſayle, and as it were, with the Spring tide of affection, ſo long as the ſtreame runnes in the due channell. And if there bee great occaſions for great motions, then it is fit the affections ſhould riſe higher, as to
<hi>burne with zeale, to be ſicke of love,</hi> to be <hi>more vile for the Lord,</hi> as <hi>David,</hi> to be counted out of our wits, with Saint
<hi>Paul,</hi> hereby to further the cauſe of Chriſt, and the good of ſoules. It was a quicke anſwer that <hi>Luther</hi> gave
<hi>Eraſmus,</hi> he told <hi>Luther, you are too hot Luther,</hi>
                  <q rend="inline">Bee it ſo "<hi>Eraſmus</hi> in your judgement, but the judge of all the world, who hath loved mee with a love as ſtrong as death, for whoſe cauſe I am <hi>exceeding</hi> zealous, will not tell me one day, <hi>Martin thou waſt too hot:</hi>
                  </q> But it is to be doubted, He will ſay rather, <hi>Eraſmus thou waſt too cold.</hi> Away with theſe midling men, dangerous perſons, who ſay, others have too much zeale, becauſe they have none at all. Maſter
<note n="*" place="margin">On Rev. 3. ver. 15, 16. <hi>Mediocritas hic eſt peſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma nihil in te mediocre eſſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſum totum ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>um to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum de ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dero. Jero. Ep.</hi> 15. <hi>ult.</hi> 181. <hi>Vide Lact. lib.</hi> 6.
<hi>ca</hi> 16. <hi>Min. Felix. p.</hi> 25. <hi>line</hi> 36. <hi>in folio.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Brightman</hi> leſſons them very well, ſo doe two or three more, they ſhall doe well to obſerve it, that they may prevent a
<hi>curſe,</hi> a <hi>ſpuing out.</hi> I can but point to the Margin, adding this to the line; Bleſſed be God for thoſe <hi>Governors of Iſrael,</hi> who were the more forward in the cauſe of God, the more backward others were; that offered <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves willingly</hi> among the people. And bleſſed bee God for the people that offered themſelves ſo
<hi>willingly</hi> alſo: And for their <hi>zeale</hi> (which ſhamed the Prieſts) for it is <hi>much,</hi> but the Lord encreaſe it yet more, and make it yet more hot and more boyling in, and for the cauſe of Chriſt, for
<hi>He is worthy.</hi> How ever it fareth with the world, it ſhall bee well with them, for the hearts of all that are good are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all ſuch, that have offered themſelves willingly. And (which is their ſecuritie) the eyes of the Lord are towards them <hi>for good,</hi> who would ſtand up for His cauſe againſt a crooked and perverſe generation; It ſhall be well with all ſuch, though they be ſmitten vvith the tongue and hand both, yet it ſhall be well: The <hi>Lord will remember all thoſe for good,</hi> Amen. Now vve goe on.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:112349:36"/>
                  <q rend="inline"> "In my underſtanding the ſtate of Religion hath never been vvorſe ſince the Reformation, then this preſent yeare, ſo the Doctor ſaith.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I ſay firſt, he anſwers himſelfe; <hi>in my underſtanding</hi> ſaith he; he is but one man, his
<hi>underſtanding</hi> muſt not be a <hi>Standard,</hi> vvhereat to meaſure the judgement of other men, in ſo high and daintie a cauſe, vvherein the <hi>glory</hi> of God is ſo much concerned. Thouſands there are vvho un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand themſelves as vvell as he, vvho know it to bee cleane contrary.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Seemeth the ſtate of Religion never vvorſe than now at this preſent time? Yes; So it vvas in ancient time, know vve not this
<hi>of old</hi> vvhen <hi>Iſrael</hi> vvas in <hi>Egypt?</hi> They had never a vvorſe opinion of their ſtate, then vvhen it vvas beginning to mend. Then they vvere comming out of their <hi>furnace,</hi> I ſay, then, vvhen they thought themſelves plunged deeper in: Then they exclaymed againſt
<hi>Moſes;</hi> O how they ſparkled and kindled againſt <hi>Moſes!</hi> juſt as vve doe againſt our <hi>Nobles</hi> and Worthies: hee had done them the greateſt vvrong and diſſervice that could bee done. Why ſo? Becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> vvould bring them out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> But vvho murmured ſo? vvho vvas ſo uncivill? The ignorant multitude. True, they did complaine of their bleſſings, and murmured vvith meate in their mouth; But upon enquiry you vvill finde, that <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Mirian</hi> murmured, theſe ſtrove alſo; The <hi>Brother</hi> and the <hi>Siſter</hi> contended and chid vvith <hi>Moſes;</hi> and if ſiſters chide vvith their brothers, they will chide bitterly. Adde vve hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, What vvas intimated before, and muſt needs cauſe a ſeeming confuſion in things;
<q rend="inline">"The Church-mans Idols are ſmitten at; then vve muſt expect that he vvill rage as they did, vvhen <hi>Stephen</hi> aſſured them touching the alteration of things;</q> the caſting out of beggerly rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and how they had perſecuted their brethren and Teachers;
<note place="margin">Act. 7.54.</note>
                  <hi>When they heard theſe things, they were cut to the heart, and they gnaſhed on him with their teeth.</hi> VVe goe on as followeth.
<q rend="inline">"<hi>So farre things are ſet backe.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I anſwer firſt, by queſtioning, how farre backe?
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:112349:36"/> Things are not ſet farther backe this yeare, then as they have beene alwayes, and ever vvill be vvhile
<hi>Reformation</hi> comes on. It pluckes downe firſt, and caſteth forth the <hi>rubbiſh,</hi> and all this vvhile, behold nothing but ruines. True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every mans <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> as well as <hi>Davids,</hi> if raiſed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to right order and rule, muſt be raiſed out of <hi>ruins.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the building never vvent up before it vvent firſt backe, and fell downe even to the ground, and into ruins. Touching this more anon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I aske againe, are things ſet backe? Certainly no; that is a deceit; the Doctor is quite miſtaken. Things doe not goe backe, vve go backe. The hearts of the children of men pull back the more ſtrongly, the more Reformation drawes on, and vvith the more ſtrength. If Reformation comes on, my heart drawes backe mightily, and I cannot thinke I ſtand ſingle in the vvorld. My heart may be an embleme vvherein to behold the
<hi>Cloyſter</hi> and <hi>Colledge</hi> both. I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, things goe not backe, <hi>Reformation</hi> is not ſet backe; vvee turne backe like a deceitfull bow, and the more ſtrongly, the more Reformation comes on.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I aske againe, are things ſet backe? They are; vvho ſets them backe, but they vvho ſhould put to both their ſhoulders to the ſetting them forward? It vvas ſo in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times. Who ſet deliverance backe, vvhen a <hi>delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> vvas ſent unto them, but the
<hi>Iſraelites</hi> themſelves vvith their owne hands? So, vvhen the
<hi>deliverer</hi> came forth of <hi>Zion,</hi> vvho oppoſed Him? The Rulers;
<note place="margin">Joh. 7.48.</note>
                  <hi>Have any of the Rulers beleeved in Him?</hi> The chiefe <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Scribes;</hi> Were they obedient? No, All theſe oppoſed Reformation vvith all their power; theſe profeſſed themſelves the moſt bitter enemies thereunto. The
<hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Scribes,</hi> they (for the moſt part) that
<hi>Are</hi> (we cannot ſay properly, they live, but <hi>are</hi>) in
<hi>Cathedralls, Cloyſters, Colledges,</hi> theſe draw backe mightily, (and cauſe others ſo to doe) when Reformation goes forward.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vatia hic ſitus eſt non diu vixit ſed diu fuit. Sen.</hi>
                  </note> So it hath beene in all ages; whether not ſo now let others judge. I vvill tell my obſervation, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans that vvill obſerve, vvhich is this; Thoſe places vvhere are <hi>Cathedralls,</hi> are as barren to the ſoules of men,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:112349:37"/> as that earth is, under which the Mines of Gold and Silver are, nothing growes thereon (ſay the Naturaliſts) for the uſe of man, no not ſo much as a graſſe for meate to beaſts. Then there muſt needs be a <hi>drawing backs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. We may note, that the Lord doth ſeeme to goe backe, when He meanes to goe forward with might and power: And when He reſolves to doe the greateſt matters for His Church, He then ſo ſeemes to ſtand, that the Church cannot eaſily judge whether He meanes to goe forward or backward, whether He be <hi>for the Church or for her adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 5.13.</note> when the Churches burdens were ſoreſt, then her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance was neareſt, when her groanes were ſtrong, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of cruell Taskmaſters, then <hi>Moſes</hi> came, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance went on a maine, and in full ſtrength: Then in the laſt place, becauſe,</p>
               <p n="5">5. This falling to <hi>ruines</hi> firſt; This
<hi>ſetting backe</hi> of things is a great <hi>offence</hi> in our way, Let us conſider this with all our hearts, that we may not ſtumble at it. What
<hi>ſetting backe</hi> is here? Take it to the utmoſt extent that can be, and yet it is no other but as the Lord Chriſt was <hi>ſet back</hi> in His way to glory. He went on the <hi>left-hand</hi> as farre <hi>back</hi> as poſſibly could be, before he ſate downe on the <hi>Right hand of the Majeſtie on High.</hi> To expreſſe it as well as I can; The Lord Chriſt went a <hi>back-way</hi> to His Throne; He
<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.9.10.</note>
                  <hi>that is now aſcended up above all Heavens, is the ſame, that deſcended firſt into the lower parts of the earth.</hi> A back-way to glory ſure. He was
<hi>ſet-backe</hi> ſo farre as is the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and that we ſometimes call <hi>Hell;</hi> and yet this <hi>backe-way</hi> was the ready way to His <hi>Crowne,</hi> to His glory. Can the Church diſlike this way, which Her Lord Chriſt hath gone before her in, and paved out unto her, though ſeemingly a backe and contrary vvay? Certainly the Church and every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber there muſt be made conformable to their Head, even in their way to Glory. They muſt be ſet backe and back, and yet farther backe. How farre backe? Even to the place of Dragons; they may daſh upon <hi>hell</hi> it ſelfe, that low bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, before they riſe up to their crowne. And yet this
<hi>backe-way,</hi> this unſearchable, and admirable way,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:112349:37"/> though it ſeemes an uncomfortable way, even as the ſhadow of death, yet ſhall it yeeld as much comfort as can be conceived, for the farther backe now, the farther forward anon; the lower the deſcent, the higher the aſcent. It vvas the way that Chriſt went in before, and all His muſt follow Him in the ſame way after; The old and ancient vvay it is, from the Croſſe to the Crowne, from the lower parts of the earth to the higheſt Heavens; from Hell to Glory. It is well with the
<hi>Body,</hi> the Church, if ſhe be as the Lord Chriſt her head: But ſhe knowes it is vvell vvith her Head, yet He vvas ſet backe, as farre backe as can be imagined, and from thence tooke His riſe to Glory. It is the Churches vvay alſo, a back-way and darkeſome, <hi>but</hi> (in that way God is moſt glorious) <hi>leading to the inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 24.26</note> The vvords fit very vvell, and doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford a ſtrong conſolation; <hi>ought not the Church to have ſuffered theſe things, and to enter into her Glory?</hi> This vvill give full anſwer to this <hi>ſetting backe,</hi> if farther backe then yet things are. The Church may be <hi>ſet-backe</hi> as farre as the gates and ſuburbes of Hell; ſhee may be ſmitten into <hi>the place of Dragons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 31.</note> and yet all this vvhile be in her vvay to her higheſt preferment: The Church can comfort her ſelfe in theſe vvords; and vvill conſider this vvithall, that, though a man hath beene ſmitten at the Altar, vvhether he did flie for refuge, yet it is rare to ſee a man ſmitten to death, vvhom God hath truely humbled, and brought upon his knees. My meaning is; vve doe not reade, that God ever deſtroyed <hi>a praying people,</hi> though things ſeeme to that people much <hi>ſet backe.</hi> I goe on now, for I muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Reſpects, In reſpect: firſt;</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <q rend="inline">I. "Of the greatneſſe of diſtractions, vvhich have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided us all one from another.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Not all; yet curſed be all that have ſo diſtracted us, for thereby they bare rule, and are multiplyed, We ſay againe, and ſay truely,
<hi>not all.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Divide &amp; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>pera.</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> ſtand out now, and are as diſcernable as is the right hand from the left: But joyned vve are now the cloſer together, the <hi>Good</hi> vvith the
<hi>Good,</hi> the <hi>Bad</hi> vvith the <hi>Bad:</hi> The <hi>good</hi> hold vvith the <hi>good,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:112349:38"/> never faſter; the <hi>Bad</hi> are joyned with the <hi>Bad</hi> never cloſer, like the ſcales of the
<hi>Leviathan,</hi> they ſticke together, that they cannot be ſundered:
<note place="margin">Job 41.17</note>
                  <hi>But into their ſecret let my ſoule never come; Into their aſſembly mine honour be not thou uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: for in their anger they ſlew a man, and in their ſelfe-will they digged downe a wall. Curſed be their anger, for it was fierce, and their wrath, for it was cruell: Lord divide them in jacob, and ſcatter them in Iſrael,</hi> Amen.<note place="margin">Gen. 49.6.</note> So much be ſaid in
<hi>Reſpect</hi> of our deſtractions. The ſecond followes, In Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of;</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <q rend="inline">II. "The multitude of Sects and Sectaries, men are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their opinions; ſo many heads, ſo many conceits, every man has his way.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I anſwer firſt, <hi>Sects</hi> there are amongſt us, not a <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> we hope: and theſe that are, (the greateſt part of them in my obſervation, which is not ſlight) are occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which is called, The <hi>Divine Service.</hi> I forbeare, but handle it and ſee, whether it be not all <hi>fleſh,</hi> no
<hi>ſpirit</hi> at all: And the Lord looke upon this cauſe, and the
<hi>offence</hi> it hath cauſed, and <hi>require</hi> it, He will doe it. Onely let this be remembred in the meane time, that it may bee now as once it was; <hi>After the way which ſome call hereſie, ſo worſhip they the God of their fathers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 24.14.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Are there Sects? A multitude ſaith the Doctor. An infallible ſigne that light and truth is appearing in more Glory. Why? Becauſe that <hi>Sects</hi> appeare, becauſe the thoughts of men are diſcovered. Certainly, we conclude and aſſure our ſelves, becauſe it is ſo, Therefore the
<note place="margin">Pſal. 102. 1 Cor. 16.19.</note>
                  <hi>Lord is building up Sion, therefore He is appearing in His Glory. A great doore and effectuall, is opened.</hi> What followes? <hi>And there are many adverſaries,</hi> as good a ſigne as can bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Are there multitude of Sects? Yes, he might as well have ſaid, a <hi>multitude of Rattle-heads.</hi> And what if there be a multitude of theſe? Shall we attribute this to the zeale of the Reformers? God forbid; for then wee ſhould lay blame upon Chriſt Himſelfe. When Hee came, did Hee
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.12.</note>
                  <hi>give peace on earth?</hi> Nay, rather <hi>Diviſions.</hi> Diviſions in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:112349:38"/> opinion, Diviſions in affection, <hi>five in one houſe,</hi> all divided and at difference about points of Religion; The <hi>father divided againſt the ſonne, the ſonne againſt the father, &amp;c.</hi> one thought, this and the other that: It was ſo, and it muſt bee ſo: <hi>There muſt be hereſies among you, that they which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved may be made manifeſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19.</note> The third Reſpect followes, and in that <hi>Reſpect</hi> his Zeale boyles up and ſcaldeth.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <q rend="inline">III. "In Reſpect of the doſhonours done to the <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God</hi> with ſo much ſcorne and ſcandall to
<hi>Religion,</hi> that in forraine parts they queſtion whether all this time we have had <hi>any.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Any what? if he relates to the former Antecedent, <hi>The ſervice of God</hi> (in charitie we will thinke ſo) by which hee meanes our
<hi>Liturgy</hi> (as now it is) then we grant that it may be queſtioned at home and abroad, whether that be <hi>The Divine ſervice</hi> or not. And truely if I might conclude the point (it is not ſo ſpirituall, nor in the clouds, too high for me) I ſhould conclude, <hi>It is not,</hi> not the
<hi>Divine Service,</hi> as ſome ſeeme to make it, even the chiefe, or whole <hi>Service of God.</hi> Truly I queſtion much whether it be a
<hi>Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> or a part of the ſame, which yet onely is ſpoken againſt hitherto, and oppoſed at this time. And yet farre be it from any ſober man to juſtifie any carriage which may bring ſcandall to Religion; ſuch as is not decent and according to rule. In the ſecond place;</p>
               <p>2. I ſay, if we of the common ſort are in an
<hi>extreame,</hi> too hot and eager for the caſting out of this
<hi>Liturgy,</hi> if wee are ſo; It is becauſe the contrary perſons are in an <hi>extreame</hi> alſo, hot and zealous for the keeping of it in. Hence our troubles and diſturbances in the Church; this the chiefe, if not the onely cauſe of the ſame, let us beare one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; Some there are, well knowne, and their folly is made manifeſt who have made that <hi>Service Booke</hi> an Idoll, have ſo honored it, have ſo advanced it, have ſo adored it: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have ſome on the other ſide uſed it like an
<hi>Idoll,</hi> have defiled and diſgraced it what they could. The Lord looke upon this controverſie and judge betwixt us and them. Who am I that I ſhould judge anothers ſervants? he ſtands or falls to his owne maſter. But theſe three things I dare
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:112349:39"/> confidently affirme. 1. That the greateſt part of theſe Sects, and all theſe troubles have beene occaſioned by this Service Booke; and woe to them by whom the offence commeth. 2. That ſuch affronts (let another call them diſhonours, indignities, or abuſes) had not beene offered thereunto, had not the adverſe party made that Booke an Idoll.
3. That thoſe, who have had a zeale for the caſting out this Booke, perhaps not ſo well tempered with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, yet can ſay as once in a different caſe, <hi>In the integrity of our hearts, and innocency of our hands have we done this.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 20.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>3. In the laſt place I anſwer, it cannot be imagined that ſo learned and grave a Divine can referre that <hi>any</hi> (as Grammer requires) to the other Antecedent, <hi>Religion,</hi> for what if Boyes and Girles or other ruder perſons will not know their <hi>Rule</hi> nor will walke by it; can it be conceived, that friends at home or ſtrangers abroad will queſtion a whole <hi>Nation</hi> for this, whether they <hi>had any Religion at all?</hi> Should friends or ſtrangers doe ſo, they would put it out of all queſtion, that they had neither Religion nor Charitie neither, who could queſtion a whole Nation ſo raſhly. I ſhall ſay no more to thoſe words till the Doctour ſhall cleare them, what he meanes by <hi>Gods ſervice:</hi> If he meanes the <hi>ſervice of God indeed;</hi> that which is truely called ſo, I am confident it is not poſſible for him to cleare this to the world; That the former, or this preſent yeare, <hi>Diſhonours have beene done thereunto.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Concluſion and Reſpects mentioned in the former Section are reſerved for this.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>ANd now I have cleared my way of this Rubbiſh, and a
<hi>Concluſion</hi> alſo <hi>Diametrally</hi> contrary to the Doctors words all along, which is agreeable to the mind of God, and to the
<hi>underſtanding</hi> of the Godly. You ſhall have it preſently, but firſt, let the
<note place="margin">Pſal. 149.6</note>
                  <hi>high praiſes of our God be in our</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:112349:39"/> 
                  <hi>mouth. Bleſſed be God the Father of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath given His ſervants, our worthies, one heart, and one way. And bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſed be theſe worthies, who have offered themſelves willingly in the cauſe of their God, promoting the ſame with much zeale and much diligence. This being premiſed, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is this.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer.
32.29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">"That the ſtate of Religion hath never beene better; hath never had more power, more life in it ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, then it hath had theſe laſt two yeares. Nay I will goe farther backe. Religion hath never beene in ſuch a way to advancement, to an exaltation, ſince the the day that Chriſt was carried up in a cloud to His Glory, then this preſent yeare.</q> The Reſpects follow, for I follow his order, not very good, becauſe I doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude firſt, and prove after as he doth. In Reſpect firſt;</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">"That things are carried in a way ſo contrary to <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>reaſon,</hi> and yet carried on.</q> The
<hi>Finger,</hi> the <hi>Hand,</hi> nay the <hi>whole Arme</hi> of God is here; His ſtrength and power is put forth here, that is out of queſtion, when there is no more <hi>probabilitie,</hi> that the meanes can attaine the end, then what makes it onely <hi>poſſible</hi> to an Almightie Arme. Secondly in Reſpect;</p>
               <p>II. <hi>That things are ſet backe, and yet farther backe.</hi> A great ſigne that Reformantion goes on, and ſhall goe on; and Religion is advancing now, and in her aſcending line. Why? Becauſe that has beene the manner alwayes, and the Lord Chriſt went backe and backe, even to that place we call <hi>Hell,</hi> and by that backe way, by that deſcending line, He aſcended to His Glory.</p>
               <p>III. Thirdly, <hi>In Reſpect of thoſe diſtractions</hi> amongſt us; No other, but what Chriſt hath commanded, and will have when Reformation ſhall come on. As He concerning Himſelf, the ſame we may ſay of <hi>Reformation</hi> in His Name. <hi>It comes not to ſend peace but a Sword;</hi> to ſet men <hi>at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> one againſt another<note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 10.34,35.</note>. It comes to ſend fire on the earth; It doth not give <hi>peace,</hi> but rather <hi>diviſions</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 12.49.51.</note>. Wee may record our Lords words with trembling, and yet every faithfull ſoule can rejoyce too; <hi>Every kingdome divided</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:112349:40"/> 
                  <hi>againſt it ſelfe is brought to deſolation</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 12.25.</note>. Certainly our divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are not a deſtructive ſigne, not a ſigne of deſolation, but a ſigne of good to all that are good. Our kingdome is not divided againſt it ſelfe, rather one kingdome divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt another; The Kingdome of <hi>Darkeneſſe</hi> againſt the kingdome of <hi>Light.</hi> And the clearer this light, the more manifeſt the <hi>oppoſers</hi> of it. Againe, theſe Diviſions are of an uniting nature, they tend to
<hi>unitie,</hi> and ſetting us in joynt againe: Now they that <hi>feare the Lord ſpeake often one to another:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> and amongſt them there is a firmer union then ever. Now the wicked <hi>are folden together as Thornes, they make a tumult</hi> now,<note place="margin">Nah.
1.11.</note> as once they did a little before they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>as dung for the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> they are taking craftie counſell againſt His people and conſulting againſt His <hi>hidden</hi>
                  <hi>ones:</hi> What followes now? As once it was, and ever will be in ſuch diſtractions and ſeeming confuſion in perſons and things; ſtrong prayers are put up againſt theſe adverſaries. Now the godly give themſelves to prayer, and they caſt not away their confidence; ſaying,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.6.</note>
                  <hi>yet God is good to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, yet have I ſet my King upon My holy hill of Sion:</hi> Yet the Lord Chriſt He is King, and His kingdome ſhall bee advanced, and his enemies ſhall He daſh to peeces like a potters veſſell, by thoſe very meanes, by which His ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies would dethrone Him, not ſuffering Him to beare rule in the world. Fourthly in Reſpect of;</p>
               <p>IIII. <hi>The Sects and Sectaries among us.</hi> Doe they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare? A ſure and certaine ſigne that God is <hi>appearing in His Glory.</hi> Laſtly in reſpect of, and that is the chiefeſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and hath in it the quinteſſence of all, in Reſpect of;</p>
               <p>V. Thoſe <hi>honours</hi> (for I take the Doctors word, willing to goe as contrary to him as he goes to the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Word of truth)
<q rend="inline">"Thoſe honours that have beene done this preſent yeare to the <hi>ſervice of God,</hi> truely called ſo and ſo indeed.</q> Can they point us to a time, our enemies themſelves being Judges, when the day of the Lord; The <hi>ſervants</hi> and <hi>ſervice</hi> of the Lord have beene more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then the former and this preſent yeare? Many Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have done worthily, but this hath exceeded them all,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:112349:40"/> in their <hi>honours</hi> done to the
<hi>ſervice of God.</hi> And now I have ſaid this, I have ſaid all: For, honour God, and His <hi>ſervice,</hi> and what would we have more? Thankes be to God for their much <hi>zeale</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> this way; And God grant they may abound yet more in their <hi>zeale</hi> for the worke of the Lord, and in giving <hi>honours</hi> to His Name, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SICT. XX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>God hath wrought wonderfully for His Church this preſent yeare. The Citie writes the remarkables upon the <hi>Pillar</hi> with a pen of Iron; ſhe <hi>nameth</hi> the Pillar, and <hi>dedicates</hi> the ſame.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>ANd now after this contention, this is eaſily cleared to the world, that ſome notable things have bin done this preſent yeare alſo, for and in behalfe of the Church. The Citie then may goe on and write the remarkables of this yeare alſo; What remarkables? Theſe which the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary allowes her. Alas what are theſe but <hi>diſtractions</hi> and
<hi>feares, wars,</hi> and <hi>rumours of wars?</hi> Yes, ſomething elſe, which are theſe, <hi>That the adverſary conceived chaffe, and brought forth ſtubble; That their owne breath as fire did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 33.11</note> That the lips of a foole have ſwallowed up himſelfe. That the adverſaries plotted and plotted, and the Lord brake their ſnares, and diſcovered their plots; That the adverſary
<hi>girded</hi> himſelfe, and <hi>girded</hi> himſelfe, it is twice repeated:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.12. Eſa. 8.9.10</note> And the Lord brake him to peeces ſo often, and more, for it is thrice repeated, and this yeare fulfilled in our eyes.
<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note>
                  <hi>The adverſaries tooke councell together, but the Lord brought it to nought, they ſpake the word, but it did not ſtand.</hi> How ſo? it followes, for <hi>God is with His people:</hi> All this muſt be written firſt, for thus it was done. Then the Church will write according to her adverſaries allowance, all the forementioned, for they followed cloſe at the heele, very <hi>Paradoxes</hi> all along, things managed by an Almightie hand for her weale againſt all
<hi>ſence</hi> and <hi>reaſon:</hi> She writes her <hi>diſtractions,</hi> for theſe united her; her <hi>feares,</hi> for theſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:112349:41"/> quieted her; <hi>violent deeds</hi> againſt her peace and dignitie, theſe awakened her, and ſet her people upon their Watch-Towers: <hi>devouring words,</hi> theſe in ſtead of ſwallowing up, preſerved her, and ſo the <hi>poyſon of Aſpes</hi> embalmed her name for ever, This muſt be recorded to all Generations.</p>
               <p>The Church can go on and write, what the Lord will do in after times. That ſhe cannot you will ſay: Yes ſhe can; for ſhe <hi>holds faſt the confidence</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 3.6.</note>, That by
<hi>the greatneſſe of Thine arme her enemies ſhall be as ſtill as a ſtone</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 15.16.</note>; He who hath wrought that and this the former yeare; This and that this preſent yeare, He will doe yet more: He will make the adverſaries of his Church to be as <hi>ſtill as a ſtone.</hi> Hee that brought His Church out of Egypt, did not forſake them at the Sea. To thinke now, that the Lord will make a ſtand here, and lift up the right hand of His adverſaries, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to forget the yeares of the
<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.10.</note>
                  <hi>Right hand of the moſt High,</hi> theſe wonderfull yeares by-paſt. Such a thought were to provoke the Lord as they did at the <hi>Sea,</hi> even at the Red-<hi>Sea.</hi> But I will not call off our thoughts from what the Lord hath done,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 83.18.</note>
                  <hi>That men may know, that thou whoſe Name alone is Jehovah, art the moſt high over all the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then, the Citie will name this <hi>Pillar.</hi> What can ſhe call it but a <hi>Pillar?</hi> Yes, it muſt have a more proper Name as anciently it had, when the <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> were diſcomfited, it muſt be called EBEN-EZAR, <hi>hitherto hath the Lord helped us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 7.12.</note> Maugre the Malice and rage of the adverſary yet HITHERTO. Notwithſtanding the power and policie of the enemy, yet HITHERTO <hi>the Lord hath helped us.</hi> Over this <hi>Wall</hi> (that is not high enough) over this <hi>Hill,</hi> and that <hi>Mountaine;</hi> through that gulfe, and thoſe ſtraites; All along backwayes, and crooked pathes; hard by the dennes of Lions, and mountaines of the Leopards, hath the Lord brought His Church HITHERTO. Bleſſed be His Name.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſhe will <hi>Dedicate</hi> this Pillar alſo. To whom? Not to man; not to his wiſedome, nor to his might; though yet ſhe will give as much to Man, as he is capable of. Her heart is loyall, choyce, and chaſt too. It cannot
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:112349:41"/> be <hi>Raviſhed</hi> (it is the Doctors word) but with the loving kindneſſe of a God; nor is it <hi>indeared</hi> to any thing but to her <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The Citie will dedicate this Pillar to the KNOWNE GOD: <hi>knowne by executing judgements, and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wing mercies.</hi> This is all, but the muſt write this in Braſſe, and with a pen of Iron, in Capitall Letters, that he who runs may reade them, and the generations to come may looke on, and ſay, <hi>What hath Jehovah done for our fathers?</hi> Wee their children will truſt in him. <hi>Amen.</hi> This <hi>Pillar</hi> will be an ornament to the Citie, the moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming and ſpecious that ever was ſeene in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Adverſary is offended hereat; better pleaſed with a
<hi>pile</hi> of Images, then with a <hi>pillar</hi> erected for
<hi>praiſe.</hi> This <hi>Treatiſe</hi> with Gods bleſſing upon it may informe him and make him wiſer; It is concluded with two words to little children, that they may account theſe <hi>Idoll-pictures</hi> fit to be played with now, and to be caſt out hereafter.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Adverſaries now (I meane not the Croſſes Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, I ſuppoſe them reaſonable men, and reaſonably well ſatisfied; but the Adverſaties) will never yeeld to us at this point. They are as ſtiffe againſt <hi>Pillars</hi> to be erected for prayſe, as they are for Images to be erected for Prayer. No matter what they are <hi>for,</hi> or
<hi>againſt; The workes of the Lord are great ſought out of all thoſe, that have pleaſure therein:</hi> And the word of the Lord is mightie, and will be ſharpe in the hearts of the Kings enemies: Such are they, who turne His glory into a lie. So the Lord hath ſaid more then once or twice in this Treatiſe. If we ſhall walke <hi>contrary</hi> thereunto, He will walke contrary to us; and then woe unto us; nothing can be for us, or proſper in our hands, for,
<note place="margin">Job. 9.13.</note>
                  <hi>if He withdraw not his anger, the proud helpers do ſtoope under Him.</hi> And ſo we have our leſſon alſo.</p>
               <p>To conclude, here is as much alſo yeelded for
<hi>ornament,</hi> as can be by Scripture allowance; if they will have more,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:112349:42"/> if nothing will ſerve them but the cunning crafts-mans worke (who ventureth to make his god with his owne fingers) and ſo they will carve for themſelves, be it at their perill; They have to doe with a jealous God, who will famiſh all the gods of the earth, their Carvers, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers all three: So He ſaith alſo. Let them be well ware of that, and remember they have a faire warning. I have done, ſo ſoone as I have ſpoken two words to the little children; they muſt not be forgotten here; for,</p>
               <p>Children will be prying herein I am ſure, becauſe here is talke of <hi>golden</hi> Croſſes, and <hi>gilded</hi> Images; they love to be gazing thereon: And very fit gazing worke it is for them, ſo long as they play with rattles and wipe their Noſes on their ſleeves. Two words will ſerve their: turne to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them for hereafter; the one ſhall be
<hi>Counſell,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>Prayer,</hi> as ſhort both as may be, for their memories are ſhort; The counſell is;
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.21.</note>
                  <hi>Little Children, keepe your ſelves from Idolls, Amen.</hi> The <hi>Prayer</hi> is as ſhort, but it muſt be continued, while our mouthes are open, for our ſelves and ours;
<hi>from dumbe Idols, from Idol-Miniſters; from brutiſh and unreaſonable men,</hi> good Lord deliver us. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 64. Line 11. reade thus.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">II "The multitude of Sects and Sectaries, which cry indeed as the Jewes before them, <hi>The Temple of the Lord,</hi> but with a worſe addition, <hi>That the Temple of the Lord may be deſtroyed.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Page 65. Line 6. manifeſt, adde this,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, doth not the Doctor wrong theſe Sectaries? Truely I thinke he doth. As he makes them more in number then they are, ſo he makes them ſpeake, what they ſpeake not; nay, what they abhorre to ſpeake. I am confident his <hi>Heritiques</hi> ſay not, <hi>Lot the temple of the Lord be pulled downe;</hi> but the contrary: <hi>Let the Temple of the Lord be built up.</hi> Let the Altars, the Rayles, the mock-gods there, let theſe be put downe, which the <hi>light</hi> Prieſts and <hi>treacherous</hi> Prophets, and <hi>bold</hi> Chancellors have built up. Downe with theſe even to the ground: So they ſay, in a zeale to Gods Glory, and doubtleſſe their zeale is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to knowledge. The, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112349:42"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
